<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Staghorn</title>
    <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog" />
    <updated>2019-10-21T19:31:22+11:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Introduction to The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/sapir-whorf-basics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/sapir-whorf-basics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T16:29:08+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/12/toki-pona-text.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>A brief introduction to the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis, linguistic relativism, and polysemy</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/12/toki-pona-text.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>A brief introduction to the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis, linguistic relativism, and polysemy</em></p>

<p id="mcetoc_1dnhm8e918">Today let’s pitch the <em>Linguistic Relativists</em> against the <em>Linguistic Universalists</em> via Toki Pona’s use of colour.</p>
<p><strong> </strong><u>The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</u></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“one's language determines one's conception of the world”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This linguistic hypothesis claims that not only do we externally vocalise our perceptions and thoughts in a manner dictated by the characteristics and breadth of our language, but that we also internally frame our thoughts in a manner dictated by our language.</p>
<p>The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis (SWH), the implications of which are often referred to as <em>Linguistic Relativity</em>, arose from the 19<sup>th</sup> and 20<sup>th</sup> century writings of Edward Sapir and Benjamin Lee Whorf (amongst others). The history of this school of thought is, as one can expect from the anthropology of the era, <em>dripping</em> in racism and notions of European political and intellectual supremacy. Nevertheless, the SWH discussed in isolation does lend itself to interesting conversations. As such I’m not going to talk much about the analysis of linguistic relativity with regards to the Inuit or Hopi peoples, because I feel that I lack the sufficient skills to extract the useful knowledge from what is otherwise a dumpster fire of flaming racist garbage.</p>
<p>So I shall return to the SWH. For this, I will choose to use the terminology I am more familiar with, that of neurology and psych:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Perception</strong> = The process of observing/being aware of an external world object stimulus and internalising it through the senses and pathways of thought to conscious and unconscious mind. “see an apple, think an apple”</li>
<li><strong>External Object</strong> = The external ‘thing’, the <em>noumenon</em>, the “apple”</li>
<li><strong>Stimulus</strong> = The external physical characteristic that can be sensed: e.g. the red light reflecting off the apple, the smell of the apple, the sound wave of a voice.</li>
<li><strong>Percept</strong> = The internal <em>phenomenon</em>, constructed in the mind. The internal image. The <em>idea</em> of that specific apple in front of you.</li>
<li><strong>Cognition</strong> = The mental process of learning and understanding, as discussed in thought, memory, perception etc.</li>
<li><strong>Thought</strong> = the flow of <em>ideas</em>, <em>associations, </em>and <em>internal objects</em> leading to a conclusion about reality.</li>
</ul>
<p>When discussing the SWH we might discuss two extents of its application, the <em>strong</em> and <em>weak</em> interpretations.</p>
<p>The strong version of the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis, deemed <em>Linguistic Determinism,</em> holds that language determines the structure and limits of thought and cognition. A rather simplified example is that our percept of an ‘apple’ is different from our percept of a ‘pear’ because we have different words for them. When see an apple or pear the higher order, more abstract, processes of perception encode the stimulus to a category which it already has available. Where there is both a word for ‘apple’ and for ‘pear’ the mind has an associated category for ‘apple’ and  for ‘pear’. As such the metaphorical admin workers can file the encoded stimulus of the red light under the ‘apple’ category. Thus the external object and it’s stimulus can be represented internally via the percept of an ‘apple’. Boom! <em>That thing is an apple!</em></p>
<p>Without this linguistic category, or even a way to subdivide larger categories (e.g. <em>sweet, red, fruit</em>), we would not have the cognitive categories to interpret these different kinds of fruit as being different. We would lose the nuance of interpretation of different fruits, and thus have a word and category that referred to all fruit. (Such as the Toki Pona <em>kili</em> = ‘fruit’, ‘vegetable’, ‘mushroom’ ≈ ‘edible plant’)</p>
<p>The weak version of the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis, deemed <em>Linguistic Influence</em>, simply holds that these linguistic categories influence but do not fully define how we think. This is admittedly easier to test experimentally in a lab with test subjects of different linguistic backgrounds. For example the standard anglophone in both reading and spatial metaphor associates the flow from left to right as analogous with past to future. When asked what word comes ‘<em>before’</em> another in a sentence, anglophones look to the left. Thus when primed with horizontal cues the anglophone will more rapidly process notions of time and order. Whereas the standard sinophone associates past with up and the future with down. For the sinophone, the associations of 上 (shàng), conceptually linked to being spatially <em>up</em> and temporally <em>previous</em> (and converse 下, xià), results in faster processing in temporal questions when primed with vertical cues.  An interesting side thought about this is, do perhaps these cognitive benefits from correct priming instead result from the associations of spatial and temporal metaphor, or because of the innate process of ingrained reading direction and the processes associated with this movement. There is consensus agreement that in the examples of English and Mandarin, the two mechanisms are not unrelated. The theory holds that the direction of writing arose from the pre-existing linguistic metaphor association, rather than the other way around.</p>
<p>A similar discussion, highlighting the division between relativist and universalist thinking, is experiments about colour perception.</p>
<p>The universalists Berlin and Kay, examined 20 languages and the way they divided colour categories. They defined a colour category as being:</p>
<ol>
<li>Monolexemic (e.g. ‘orange’ as opposed to ‘yellow-red’)</li>
<li>Monomorphemic (e.g. ‘blue’ as opposed to ‘blue-ish’</li>
<li>Not a subset of greater category (e.g. ‘green not ‘emerald’ which is a subset of green)</li>
<li>Isn’t only applicable to certain objects (e.g. ‘yellow’ as opposed to ‘blonde’)</li>
<li>Is salient for all informants (e.g. “blue” as opposed to “tiffany™-colour”)</li>
</ol>
<p>Interesting they found that for languages with fewer than 11 categories, the categories always appeared in a specific pattern as the number of total categories increased. For languages with N categories, if:</p>
<ul>
<li>N = 2, ‘black’ AND ‘white’</li>
<li>N = 3, add ‘red’</li>
<li>N = 4, add ‘green’ OR ‘yellow’ but not both</li>
<li>N = 5, add ‘green’ AND ‘ yellow’</li>
<li>N = 6, add ‘blue’</li>
<li>N = 7, add ‘brown’</li>
<li>N ≥ 8, add ‘grey’ OR ‘orange’ OR ‘pink’ OR ‘purple’</li>
</ul>
<p>Interestingly colours were found to roughly refer to the same shades across languages, as noted in the Munsell Colour System (hue, value, chroma aka colour, brightness, saturation). This seems to suggest an evolutionary agreement on which colours are important to humans, or perhaps what colour stimuli we can perceive (recalling retinal and sensory neurology).</p>
<p>We find that Toki Pona has been constructed as a N = 5, language and thus has the words: (pimeja = black) (walo = white) (loje = red) (laso = green) (jelo = yellow). As a language intentionally constructed by a linguist, it’s to be expected that this selection aligns with Berlin and Kay’s model for colour evolution.</p>
<p>But the question then arises, how do we refer to other colours in N &lt; 6 languages like Toki Pona? Two handy tricks <em>polysemy</em> and use of <em>polylexemes</em>.</p>
<p>Polysemy is the coexistence of multiple meanings (<em>sememes</em>) for a word, word-group, or word-bit (<em>morpheme</em>). This can been seen in some words in modern natural languages that have since developed N &gt; 11, but may still have polysemous words from earlier in its evolution. Some such examples are included below:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Language</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>Blue/Green Polysemy</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p>Blue Monosemy</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p>Green Monosemy</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Chinese</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E9%9D%92">青</a> (qīng) </p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E8%93%9D">蓝</a> (lán)</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E7%BB%BF">绿</a> (lǜ) </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Arabic</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p> الخضراء (al-khaḍrā')</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> أزرق (azraq)</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p>أخضر (akhḍar)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Vietnamese</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>xanh</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Tswana</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>tala</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Toki Pona</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>laso</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>A polylexeme is a unit made of two lexemes rammed together, as in the example “yellow-red” to mean “orange”. Vietnamese employs a similar in its Blue/Green distinctions by adding other kinds of descriptors to the root <em>xanh:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>xanh da trời = ‘blue’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh dương = ‘sky blue / azure’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh nước biển = ‘ocean blue’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh lá cây = ‘leaf green’</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Toki Pona can employ polylemes in these two systems of mixing and describing systems:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>loje laso</em> (blue-ish red) or <em>laso loje</em> (red-ish blue) ≈ ‘purple’</li>
<li><em>jelo loje</em> (red-ish yellow) ≈ ‘orange’</li>
</ul>
<p> OR perhaps</p>
<ul>
<li><em>loje pi telo loje </em>(red of ‘red water’) ≈ ‘blood-red’</li>
<li><em>laso kasi</em> VS <em>laso pi</em> <em>telo suli </em>(blue/green of plant/leaf VS blue/green of ‘big water’) ≈ ‘leaf-green’ VS ‘ocean-blue’</li>
</ul>
<p>So whilst the <em>linguistic relativists</em> might say that these speakers of N &lt; 6 languages view colour through the lenses and combinations of the N categories of colour and thus categories of thought, the <em>linguistic universalists</em> would instead demand every culture who can gaze upon the blue ocean will have a way to conceptualise that colour distinct from the colour of a leaf, even if they have no monolexemic monomorpheme to describe it.</p>
<p>I can’t imagine there will ever be a consensus amongst the linguists, but as a someone who sits in the sidelines watching (<em>sports metaphor—ha!)</em>, it’s fun to see what happens.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from image of <em>sitelen pona</em> from <em>Toki Pona: The Language of Good</em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Jung’s Collective Unconscious &amp; Archetypes</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/jungs-archetypes/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/jungs-archetypes/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T13:34:48+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/11/archetype-text.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>A brief introduction to Jungian Analytical Psychology, the aparatuses of the psyche, the collective unconscious, and Jungian Archetypes.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/11/archetype-text.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>A brief introduction to Jungian Analytical Psychology, the aparatuses of the psyche, the collective unconscious, and Jungian Archetypes.</em></p>

<p id="mcetoc_1dnhlbveh2">A similar concept to Aarne-Thompson-Uther indices is the Swiss Psychiatrist Carl Jung’s concept of <em>Archetypes</em>. Intellectual adversary and friend to Sigmund Freud (and potential repressed but reciprocated homo-erotic object of desire), Jung presented similar but divergent thoughts on Freud’s new field of psychoanalysis. </p>
<p>Freud’s Model of the psych consisted of three psychic apparatuses:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Id (Latin: “it”)</strong> = Disorganised instinctual component constructed of desires, impulses, and drives, present from birth. Driven by the <em>Pleasure Principle</em> to seek gratification and avoiding pain. This apparatus is completely unconscious and unknown to the conscious mind.</li>
<li><strong>The Ego (Latin: “I”)</strong> = The organised, cognitive and executive component which seeks to restrain the Id by grounding itself in the reality of the world. Driven by the <em>Reality Principle</em> to seek ways to gratify the id in a way which will maximise long term pleasure and minimise pain. This is achieved by rationalization and reason. This apparatus is largely conscious and sub/preconscious.</li>
<li><strong>The Super-Ego</strong> = The internalisation of outside world’s culture and rules. The “conscience”, the Super-Ego contradicts the Id, wanting to act with decorum and is outraged and shamed by the depravity of the Id. This apparatus spans from the conscious, via the pre-conscious, into the deep unconscious.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thus Freud could discuss mental disorders as conflicts between the <em>Ego</em> and the <em>Id </em>(<em>Transference Neuroses</em>)<em>,</em> between the <em>Ego</em> and the<em> Super-Ego</em> (<em>Narcissistic Neuroses</em>)<em>,</em> and between the <em>Ego</em> and the external world (<em>Psychoses)</em>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Jung divided the psyche into the conscious <em>Ego</em>, the <em>Personal Unconscious</em> (our recalled and repressed memories), and the <em>Collective Unconscious</em>.</p>
<p>Jung’s take, informed heavily by Eastern philosophy, was that the <em>Collective Unconscious</em> was populated by human instinct and abstractions called ‘<em>Archetypes’</em>.  Jungian psychology, now termed <em>Analytic Psychology</em>, examined how the psych strove, and more often than not failed and stagnated, to pursue its goal of self-realisation via the process of individuation, the formation of a robust and whole sense of self. The interplays between states of progress in individuation and issues encountered would be seen by analysing a patient’s dreams and thoughts. Symbolic elements of dreams for example would considered the implication of these symbolic archetypes, what they meant to the patient, and how the symbolic interplay of their narrative could be interpreted as representing psychological states.</p>
<p>These archetypes are universally relatable symbols and can be considered a simplified version of Aarne-Thompson-Uther’s motifs: A great/earth mother, a wise sage, the duality of light and dark. Some of these archetypes, being abstract symbols, can over-lap or be subsets of each other, others can be mixed flavours.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="file:///Users/alexandernathan/Documents/Publii/sites/staghorn/input/media/posts/3/Venus_de_Milo_Paris_2_September_2013_001.jpg" alt="" width="2848" height="4272">
<figcaption >
<p>The "Venus de Milo" by Alexandros of Antioche, a marble sculpture of the Greek goddess Aphrodite. When discussing the Greek gods in terms of Jungian Archetypes, Aphrodite (the embodiment of love and beauty) is a projected and symbolic incarnation of internal archetypes (here being of feminine sexuality, love, and beauty) (photo by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Venus_de_Milo,_Paris_2_September_2013_001.jpg">Tom King</a>)</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>These internal archetypes are projected onto the external world as simplified way of viewing complex ideas. June Singer discussed some more well-studied archetypes in terms of opposites, one set pertaining to the <em>Ego</em> the other to the abstract notion of the <em>Shadow</em>. Light (ego) is opposed by Darkness (shadow), the Old Wise Man (ego) is opposed by the Trickster (shadow), the Great Mother (ego) is opposed by the Tyrannical Father (shadow), et cetera. The implication of the Chinese philosophy of Yin and Yang, is unmistakable.</p>
<p>Jung however would argue that the metaphysics and cosmologies of eastern philosophy, of astrology, of alchemy, of mythology, all of which he was well versed in, were simply the human psyche projecting these archetypical symbols onto external phenomena. The process of Alchemy, it’s various procedures, were imbued with the symbols of the internal psych, with the progress towards <em>The Great Work</em> of Alchemy (e.g. formation of the <em>Philosopher’s Stone) </em>marked by a progress of archetypical symbols towards <em>The Great Work</em> of personal psychology: Self-Realisation.</p>
<p>So what are these archetypes? Well given the ethereal and blended nature, delineating individual and unique archetypes is difficult, and at times down-right futile. Nevertheless a number of Jungian psychologists, mystics, artists, and anthropologists have tried.</p>
<p>In his posthumously compiled works <em>Archetypes of the Collective Unconscious</em>, Jung explicitly refers to 12 main archetypes, whilst acknowledging the existence of many others:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Self</li>
<li>The Anima</li>
<li>The Animus</li>
<li>The Shadow</li>
<li>The Persona</li>
<li>The Father</li>
<li>The Mother</li>
<li>The Child</li>
<li>The Wise Old (Sage)</li>
<li>The Hero</li>
<li>The Trickster</li>
<li>The Maiden</li>
</ul>
<p>In Margaret Mark and Carol Pearson’s book <em>The Hero and the Outlaw</em> a guide to distinct branding directed by principles of myth and pop-psychology define a different 12 archetypes:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Innocent</li>
<li>The Orphan</li>
<li>The Hero</li>
<li>The Caregiver</li>
<li>The Explorer</li>
<li>The Rebel</li>
<li>The Lover</li>
<li>The Creator</li>
<li>The Jester</li>
<li>The Sage</li>
<li>The Magician</li>
<li>The Ruler </li>
</ul>
<p>This has been used also as a system of personality typing and alignment. Largely popular personality typing systems can be considered to employ ideas of archetypes such as: personality enneagrams, various zodiacs, Myer’s Briggs personality types etc.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from an <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Greek_Eros_vase.png">attic red vase</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Introduction to Phytohormones</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/phytohormones-basics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/phytohormones-basics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T13:33:15+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/10/pothos-text.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>A brief introduction to phytohormones</em>.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/10/pothos-text.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>A brief introduction to phytohormones</em>.</p>

<p id="mcetoc_1dnhkmqrg8">Why do we prune? It helps promote more proximal growth and development of the plant, but how? The easy answer that “the plant can spend more energy on growing wide as opposed to tall”, whilst charmingly personifying doesn’t actually help to explain the increased rate of lateral growth. Furthermore it doesn’t really provide any mechanistic justification for not just simply letting your plant grow un-pruned until it has achieved the desired lateral development.</p>
<p> And yet we see pruning the most distal parts seems to promote lateral growth. Why is that? To answer this, let’s have a quick refresher on plant endocrinology.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnltjvj50"><u>Plant Hormone Basics</u></h2>
<p>There are five major groups of <em>phytohormones </em>(plant hormones) discussed in modern botany:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Abscisic Acid</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Auxins</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Cytokinins</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Ethylene</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Gibberellins</em></strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Below is a (very basic) description of what they do.</p>
<p><strong><em>Abscisic Acid</em> (ABA)</strong> is the chief water stress signal. When roots detect that water is at a critical level they release ABA into the plant vasculature. Similar to a human <em>neurotransmitters</em> and neural <em>action potential</em> functioning, ABA triggers an influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and <em>membrane depolarisation</em> of stomatal <em>guard cells</em> (the cells which open/close <em>stomata</em>, the microscopic windows in a leaf which allow water and air to be breathed in and out of the plant). This results in efflux of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, and associated anions. The loss of these ions, draws water out of the guard cells, mediating stomatal closure, reducing potential water losses by <em>transpiration</em>.</p>
<p> At this point it is worth mentioning the topic of <em>Meristems</em>, locations of embryonic plant tissue capable of dividing and growing branches/roots. <em>Meristematic</em> <em>tissue</em> can be located apically (end of stems/vines/roots) or lateral (branch points).</p>
<p><strong><em>Auxins</em></strong> care about length over width. This is to say they promote <em>apical dominance</em>, longer stems and roots with less lateral/axillary budding. Produced chiefly in the apical meristems, Auxins signal for lateral buds (dormant embryonic <em>meristems</em>) to remain dormant, causing growth to be predominantly apical rather than lateral. Thus in the case of <em>Epipremnum aureum </em>pruning, we are removing apical meristems, promoting development of lateral buds, and overall fullness of the plant, rather than length.</p>
<p> In a related manner, <em>Auxin</em> is the chief of <em>phototropism</em>, the curving growth of plants towards a light source. Produced in the stem tip, Auxin localises to the darker side of the plant. Thus, when the auxin promotes more pronounced growth on this side, the overall effect is to arch the stem towards the light. The same processes facilitates <em>gravitropism </em>(aka <em>geotropism</em>), the growth of root in the direction of gravity by gravitationally-dictated auxin distribution in the roots. This is the process which is being exploited by exogenous <em>Auxin</em> when industrial ‘Rooting Hormone’ is added to plants or cuttings.</p>
<p><strong><em>Cytokinins</em></strong> (not to be mistaken for human kinins of the <em>Kinin-Kallikrein system</em>) promote cell division and inhibit aging of greenery. Their function is far too complex to attempt even a basic discussion here, but in short, Cytokinins work in a system of balances and ratios with Auxin to drive embryonic patterning and differentiation, <em>callus</em> formation.</p>
<p><strong><em>Ethylene </em></strong>(aka Ethene in organic chemistry, H<sub>2</sub>C=CH<sub>2</sub>)  is the cause of the proverbial ‘rotten apple’ spoiling the bunch, and ripe bananas ‘infecting’ green bananas with their ripe-ness. The only known gaseous plant hormone, <em>Ethylene</em> signals for the opening of flowers, the ripening of fruit, the shedding (<em>abscission</em>) of leaves, and ultimately rotting of proverbial apples. The culmination of a series of biosynthetic operations and the <em>Methionine/Yang cycle</em> (which gives me <em>Citric Acid/Krebb’s</em> undergrad war flashbacks), <em>Ethylene</em> is formed by the oxidation of ACC. Thus the agricultural world has found that keep produce in high-CO<sub>2</sub>, low-O<sub>2</sub> environments reduces ripening and rotting.</p>
<p><strong><em>Gibberellins </em></strong>(GAs) main concern is <em>internode</em> elongation, with lesser roles in germination, differentiation, and embryonic patterning, and synthesised in areas of active plant growth. Plants with low/defective/inhibited <em>GAs</em> present with <em>brachytic</em> <em>dwarfism</em> (internodal shortening). This causes short stems and close clustering of nodes (and thus leaves/branches/flowers etc). Conversely <em>GA</em> excess results in long stems, sparse branching, and elongated plants. The understanding of this hormone plays an important role in forming high-yielding varieties of agricultural goods (dwarf cereals, elongated sugarcane).</p>
<p>So<em>, </em>whenever we hear someone discussing plant-pruning in the name of lateral growth, we can thank our little friends<em> Auxins</em> and<em> Gibberellins</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from photo by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Money_plant_(Epipremnum_aureum)_1.jpg">Mokkie</a> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Nephrolithiasis Basics</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/nephrolithiasis/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/nephrolithiasis/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T13:33:19+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/9/kidney-stones-text.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>Basic Med Student Summary of Nephrolithiasis: Causes, Epidemiology, Clinical Presentation, Diagnosis, Management, Prognosis, Complications.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/9/kidney-stones-text.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>Basic Med Student Summary of Nephrolithiasis: Causes, Epidemiology, Clinical Presentation, Diagnosis, Management, Prognosis, Complications.</em></p>

<div class="post__toc">
<h3>Table of Contents</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk6jlhe">Stone Types and Urinary Chemical Causes</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnltdiso0"> Epidemiology</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnltdobr1">Stone-Specific Risk Factors </a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnltdsqa2">Clinical Presentation and Diagnosis</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnlte9i1c">Management</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnltebsmd">Prognosis and Complications</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhk6jlhe"><u>Stone Types and Urinary Chemical Causes</u></h2>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="file:///Users/alexandernathan/Documents/Publii/sites/staghorn/input/media/posts/1/Gray1122.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1122" width="515" height="400">
<figcaption >Spatial relationship between kidneys and their neighbouring viscera</figcaption>
</figure>
<ul>
<li><strong>Calcium Oxalate (75%)</strong> ↑ Calcium ↑ Oxalate ↑ Urate ↑ Citrate
<ul>
<li>Oxalate: meat, dietary sodium, nuts, beans, cruciferous vegetables, fatty acid malabs (Crohn’s), high vit C, low B6</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Uric Acid (10%)</strong> ↑ Urate
<ul>
<li>Aciduria</li>
<li>Uric Acid: Alcohol, seafood, fatty and organ meats</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Struvite (5%)</strong> ↑ Urease Positive UTIs
<ul>
<li>Proteus mirabilis, Klebsiella, Pseudomonas UTIs</li>
<li>Form largest stones, including STAGHORN calculi (which fill the renal pelvis and calyces)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Calcium Phosphate</strong> ↑ Calcium ↑ Phosphate</li>
<li><strong>Cystine</strong> ↑ Cysteine (familial cysteinuria)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnltdiso0"> <u>Epidemiology</u></h2>
<p>General Risk Factors</p>
<ul>
<li>♂ &gt; ♀</li>
<li>30-60 years old</li>
<li>Dehydration</li>
<li>+ve FHx or PHx</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnltdobr1">Stone-Specific Risk Factors </h3>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p class="align-center"><strong> </strong></p>
</td>
<td class="align-center" width="94">
<p><strong>Risk Factors</strong></p>
</td>
<td colspan="4" width="377">
<p class="align-center"><strong>Prevention</strong></p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Calcium Oxalate</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↑ Calcium</p>
<p>↑ Oxalate</p>
<p>↑ Citrate</p>
<p>↓ Urine pH</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Sufficient Dietary Calcium*</p>
<p>↓ Oxalate Rich Food</p>
</td>
<td rowspan="2" width="94">
<p>↓ Dietary salt ↓ Animal proteins    Thiazide diuretics (for isolated  cases of ↑ urinary calcium</p>
</td>
<td rowspan="5" width="94">
<p>↑ Water</p>
<p>&gt; 2½ L/d</p>
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Calcium Phosphate</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↑ PTH</p>
<p>Type 1 RTA</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary acidisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Uric Acid</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↓ Urine pH</p>
<p>↑ Urate</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Allopurinol</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Struvite</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urease + UTI</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary acidisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>UTI prevention and treatment</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Cystine</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Cystinuria</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>* low calcium intake increases oxalate reabsorption </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="file:///Users/alexandernathan/Documents/Publii/sites/staghorn/input/media/posts/1/Gray1128.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1128" width="602" height="600">
<figcaption >A nephron schematic, because who doesn't love a good nephron schematic?</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Note that the three locations that stones are most likely to get ‘stuck’ are:</p>
<ul>
<li>the pelvi-ureteric junction (PUJ)</li>
<li>the ureter enters the pelvis (crossesing the common iliac artery bifurcation)</li>
<li>the vesicoureteric junction (VUJ)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnltdsqa2"><u>Clinical Presentation and Diagnosis</u></h2>
<ul>
<li>Symptoms
<ul>
<li>Paroxysmal progressive unilateral flank colic</li>
<li>Radiation: to lower abdomen, groin, labia, testicles, perineum</li>
<li>Haematuria</li>
<li>Nausea/Vomiting</li>
<li>Dysuria, Frequency, Urgency</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Signs
<ul>
<li>Observed haematuria</li>
<li>Reduced bowel sounds</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Investigations
<ul>
<li>WBC (?UTI)</li>
<li>BUN, Creatinine (?AKI)</li>
<li>Dipstick (?UTI, pH &gt;7 ?Urease +)</li>
<li>Urine Microscopy + Straining (?Crystals)
<ul>
<li>Dumbbell/Octahedron (?Oxalate)</li>
<li>Rhomboid/Needles (?Urate)</li>
<li>Coffin-Prism (?Struvite)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Urine Culture (?UTI)</li>
<li>Bloods (UEC, PTH, Urate, HCO3, ALP)</li>
<li>Nonenhanced CT Abdo-Pelvis (Gold-Standard)
<ul>
<li>Calculus size, site, densite, obstruction, hydronephrosis)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ultrasound (pregnant, children, gynae/abdo DDx)</li>
<li>KUB X-Ray
<ul>
<li>Radiopaque = Calcium-containing</li>
<li>Weakly + = Struvite or Cysteine</li>
<li>Radiolucent = Urate</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Intravenous pyelogram</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Differentials
<ul>
<li>Testicular torsion</li>
<li>Acute abdomen</li>
<li>Hydronephrosis</li>
<li>UTI</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnlte9i1c"><u>Management</u></h2>
<ul>
<li>?Complicated Urolithiasis
<ul>
<li>High-grade hydronephrosis</li>
<li>Pyelonephritis</li>
<li>Urosepsis</li>
<li>AKI</li>
<li>Vomiting or Intractable Pain</li>
<li>&lt; 4w of Stone Hx</li>
<li>Failed medical therapy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Stable Pt, Uncomplicated Stone, &lt;10mm
<ul>
<li>Support and Surveil</li>
<li>Hydrate</li>
<li>NSAIDs, IV Morph</li>
<li>Tamsulosin (a-blocker) or Nifedipine (CCB)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Uterorenoscopy + Extracorporal Shockwave Lithotripsy  for &lt; 20mm</li>
<li>Percutaneous Nephrolithotomy for &gt;20mm</li>
<li>Complicated Cases
<ul>
<li>Ureteral stenting or percutaneous nephrostomy (pyelo/hydro-decompression)</li>
<li>Shock Wave Lithotripsy</li>
<li>Last resort = laproscopic or open surgical removal (e.g. staghorn stones)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p id="mcetoc_1dnhk890bf">If known stone cause = Urine pH Modification</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnltebsmd"><u>Prognosis and Complications</u></h2>
<ul>
<li>&lt;5mm often to pass spontaneously,</li>
<li>&gt;10mm typically won’t, especially if ureteric sphincter or proximal.</li>
<li>50% 10 year relapse rate</li>
<li>Complications
<ul>
<li>Recurrent UTI → pyelonephritis, urosepsis, and perinephric abscess</li>
<li>Obstruction → hydronephrosis → glomerular damage</li>
<li>Acute kidney injury</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from glomerulus micrograph by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Renal_corpuscle.jpg">Ed Uthman</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What the !#%$ is the internet? &amp; Other Interrogatives</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/internet-basics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/internet-basics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T17:27:06+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/internet-what.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p>A basic introduction to the internet, what it is and who owns it, the web, ISPs, and URLs. Discussed via the medium of basic English grammar and interrogatives.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/internet-what.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>A basic introduction to the internet, what it is and who owns it, the web, ISPs, and URLs. Discussed via the medium of basic English grammar and interrogatives.</p>

<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhnds3p0"><strong>Basics of the Internet</strong></h2>
<p>A rudimentary introduction to the internet could take many forms, but instead I thought it would be whimsically inane to run through the 5 W’s (“who”, “what”, “when”, “where”, and “why”) —BUT NO— then I thought I might up-the-nonsense and take it to a linguistic place. So to investigate the internet, let’s simultaneously investigate the12 different types of interrogatives (question-askers) in English.</p>
<p>Note that the Yes/No specific questions are a bit bizarre for this purpose so we’ll get them out of the way first.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhnecp21"><strong>Interrogative Inversion</strong></h2>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhnfbdc2"><u>Using the Copula (<em>to be/is</em>)</u></h3>
<p id="mcetoc_1dnhnfqsf3" class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>Is the internet</em> [real]?”</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/man_use_keyboard-scopio-e3dac5e6-c4c9-4010-b6f2-fa776057bf70.jpg" alt="" width="5568" height="3712">
<figcaption >A royalty free stock image, because this article starts off very grammar heavy and needed pictures or two</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>To ask questions using this format, swap the verb and the subject from the statement “The internet is [real]”, to become a question “Is the internet [real]?”</p>
<p>Answer: <em>Yes. Yes it is real. At least in some senses.</em></p>
<p>In the material sense it is an emergent property of computer network interconnectivity, but not a physical entity in itself. However, discussing the metaphysical mysteries of reality or the ‘<em>real’</em>, is entirely above my (non-existent) pay-grade and beyond the scope of this article.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhnhh584"><u>Using an Auxiliary (<em>to do</em> OR <em>to have</em>)</u></h3>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>Does the internet</em> [exist]?”</p>
<p><em>Yep</em>. For sake of our discussion, let’s assume that the internet does exist, as taking the article in the direction of metaphysical solipsistic (“nothing exists external to my mind”) would hardly be that informative.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhni6ja5"><strong>Declarative Question (aka Implied Inversion)</strong></h2>
<p>This is an interesting case in English in which a statement in the <em>indicative case</em> (statement as opposed to instruction), is coded as a question by intonation. In English, this is displayed by increasing pitch at the end of a sentence. <em>“You know what I mean?”</em></p>
<p>Despite being ordered subject-verb, the intonation implies a yes/no question as if it had been ordered verb-subject.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“The internet is [good]<em>?</em>”</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/markus-spiske-8OyKWQgBsKQ-unsplash.jpg" alt="" width="5760" height="3840">
<figcaption >Royalty free stock image of some of the worst code formatting I have ever seen, but doesn't it look very computery? (Also note: doesn't it? = does not it? = [verb] [subject] = interrogative inversion)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>To ask, <em>“the internet is [good]?”, </em>or the implied <em>“is the internet [good]?”</em>, is to ask a moralistic question about an abstraction without agency. The internet doesn’t <em>do</em>, it is simply a thing we <em>use</em>.</p>
<p>We can use the internet to do good or bad things, but it in itself is as morally culpable as a <em>rock</em>, or <em>the colour blue</em>, or <em>mathematics</em>.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhniov96"><strong>Interrogative Determiners and Pronouns</strong></h2>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>What </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p>Ok, <em>now</em> we’re getting somewhere. </p>
<p>Named from a portmanteau (linguistic term for a Brangelina/Kimye-esque ‘celebrity couple name’) of ‘interconnected network’, the internet is a global network of computers sharing access and data via the <em>Internet Protocol Suite (IPS)</em>. This includes the <em>Internet Protocol (IP)</em> and the <em>Transmission Control Protocol (TCP).</em><em> </em></p>
<p>The IP is a regular system by which computer/data addresses (IP Addresses) can be encoded as a string of numbers. These numbers essentially symbolise what we could otherwise write out as “<em>The ‘website’ folder on Erin’s laptop in her bedroom in her apartment in Sydney, Australia</em>”, and <em>“George’s dusty old desktop PC in Idaho”.</em></p>
<p>The TCP is a standardised way of packaging that information to send/access to/from other computers. This is like everyone universally deciding to communicate via their facebook account, thus eliminating email, postage, morse-code, etc. In short it’s just a universal way to send and receive information to make sure all computers are on the same page in terms of how data is sent/shared. This is comparable to common language language/lingua franca if you will.</p>
<p>At a grossly simplified level, the internet is every connected computer in the world which is saying that it can send/receive information to/from every other connected computer in the world via a combination of wires and wireless transmissions. Obviously there is more info about what can/can’t be accessed and what is/isn’t shared, but in short. That is it. That is the internet.</p>
<p>You will note that this definition is different to an <em>internet browser.</em> These icons you click to go look at something “<em>on the internet”</em> are programs that interpret computer code into nice visual and readable pages for you, the user. What you see when using Google Chrome, Firefox, Internet Explorer etc, is however not ‘<em>the internet’</em> but rather a subset called the <em>‘world wide web’ (‘The Web’ aka WWW)</em>.</p>
<p>If the internet is a library (the whole building), then the web is the books. You can still meet up with people in the library to discuss research, study for exams, share casserole recipes with old ladies in knitwear, or do drugs and make out in the bathroom. You can engage in all manner of pursuits, data sharing, legal and illegal activity, but most people simply go there to look at books.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>Whose </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p>Who owns the internet? No one. Or many people. It depends who you ask and how you think of it. When we refer to the internet it is like talking about the traffic on your town’s road network, we can discuss it in terms of three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The actual roads, stop signs, traffic lights, etc</li>
<li>The many cars, bicycles, and road-enable barbie go-karts</li>
<li>The abstract flow of moving bodies which can clump and cluster and is the sum of the moving entities in the physical road space.</li>
</ol>
<p> 1) The physical network of the internet, the cables, routers, zip-zoop signal-senders, and such are owned by <em>Internet Service Providers (ISPs)</em>. The cables and sub-networks owned by ISPs physically meet at <em>Internet Exchange Points (IXPs)</em>. All of these ISP-owned-networks form the physical connective component of <em>‘the internet’</em>.</p>
<p>Note: a group of people or company can have their own little isolated network, a <em>local area network (LAN)</em>, to share documents, perhaps play local multiplayer games, or connect to printers, without the internet. These LANs can be considered an analogy for the internet. I have my pictures of puppies on my laptop. Dave has his casserole recipes on his. If we connect our two laptops with a physical linking cable (like an IXP) we can share this data between two distinctly owned entities.</p>
<p>2) The many cars on the road (owned by millions of individuals) are the many computers holding data you want. These are the databases, these are the online depositories of 90s Nokia ring-tones, these are the computers who ‘host’ the websites you want to access on the web. Thus, the contributors to internet are everyone, and in this sense the internet is owned by those individuals who use it. </p>
<p>3) The abstract ebb and flow of cars, the free-flowing availability of online data, the abstract idea of the <em>‘internet’</em> is not, and cannot be owned by anyone. As overly grand as it sounds, in this sense, the internet is not a ‘<em>thing’</em> as much as it is a method of sharing data. Much like <em>‘speech</em>’ cannot be owned (people can <em>own</em> their vocal chords, and someone can <em>own</em> the room you are speaking in), the ‘<em>internet</em>’ cannot be owned because it isn’t a <em>‘thing’</em>.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>Which </em>is the internet”</p>
<p><em>Which</em> is a good example of an interrogative, but doesn’t really apply here. So let’s use it to further discuss the internet-vs-web distinction.</p>
<p><strong> </strong>The web is a connection of available data and documents identified by <em>Uniform Resource Locators (URL), </em>frequently meshed and interlinked by <em>hypertext</em> (click through links on websites). A URL (e.g. <a href="http://www.staghorn.blog">http://www.staghorn.blog</a>) is essentially a pretty and human-friendly version of an IP (heinous string of numbers).</p>
<p>I’m sure you’ve noted the “http://” component before the “www” bit. This tells the browser being used that the web page should be received using the <em>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)</em>. This is how we can access (‘<em>view’</em>) the various texts, images, videos, songs, and any form of <em>web resource</em>, on the web.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center"> “<em>Who/Whom </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--highlight ">Recalling that <em>[who] is used in place of the [SUBJECT] </em>of the clause and that<em> [whom] </em>is used in place of the <em>[OBJECT]</em> of the clause. Just as <em>[he]</em> becomes <em>[hi<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>m</strong>]</span></em> ("He kicked the door" vs "The waitress slapped hi<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">m</span></strong>"), <em>[who]</em> becomes <em>[who<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">m</span></strong>]</em> ("Who ate the pie?" vs "She sent a letter to who<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">m</span></strong>?"). If you could substitute in <em>[hi<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>m</strong></span>]</em>, then <em>[who<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>m</strong></span>]</em> is correct.</p>
<p>In our intersection traffic metaphor, the <em>who</em> of the internet is anyone with a car (a computer). However, more accurately, we might consider the <em>who</em> of the internet to be anyone with a house that can be accessed via the metaphorical city’s street network.</p>
<p>If you have a house (computer), and you want it to be somewhere people can drive to (access on the internet), you only need to keep your doors unlocked (security details and having your computer always running), and make sure your ISP has given you a street address that people can actually find (IP/URL).</p>
<p>Thus the <em>internet</em> is the roads and traffic and the places you can go on the internet at any point in time are anywhere that is unlocked and anywhere with an address you can find.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhnl83m7"><strong>Pro-Adverbs</strong></h2>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>How </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p>So how does typing in a URL into my browser connect me to a big computer in another country so I can scroll through pictures of unlikely animal friendships?</p>
<p>A URL (<a href="http://www.staghorn.blog/buttface.html">http://www.staghorn.blog/buttface.html</a>) typically consists of three major components: a protocol (http), a hostname/domain (<a href="http://www.staghorn.blog">www.staghorn.blog</a>), and a file name (/buttface.html).</p>
<p>The hostname can contain various pieces of information, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li>That the URL encodes a site on the world wide web: “www”</li>
<li>The domain name: “staghorn”</li>
<li>Information about the location or type of host: “.blog” “.com” “.au” “.org”</li>
</ul>
<p>Whereas the file name contains specific page locations and sublocations, and can contain specific useful functions:</p>
<ul>
<li>/buttface.html = refers to a page named “buttface”, which is coded as an html file.</li>
<li>/articles/pass-times/napping.pdf = would refer to a pdf document named “napping”, from a folder “pass-times”, from a folder “articles”, from whatever domain the page is from. This is, including everything before it, referred to as a “<em>path</em>”.</li>
<li>Scripts and queries: this includes all the horrific punctuation and nonsense after the bit of the URL which is meaningless for you and me. These can range from fairly simple and uniform, to a cybernetic hellscape of site specific coding. For example:</li>
<li><a href="https://www.google.com/search?sxsrf=ACYBGNQ3ekXZlRhOyZL7-hnc1hi7qjSlHA%3A1571023196928&amp;ei=XOmjXaWqOKzgz7sPjpuh8Aw&amp;q=THIS+IS+A+QUERY+FOR+THE+SEARCH+SCRIPT&amp;oq=THIS+IS+A+QUERY+FOR+THE+SEARCH+SCRIPT&amp;gs_l=psy-ab.3..33i22i29i30.2534.19237..30617...7.1..2.377.10767.0j30j19j3......0....1..gws-wiz.....10..0i71j35i39j0i131i273j0j0i131j0i67j0i131i67j35i362i39j0i22i30.FHTxFzd76wY&amp;ved=0ahUKEwilyNi85ZrlAhUs8HMBHY5NCM4Q4dUDCAs&amp;uact=5">https://www.google.com/search?sxsrf=ACYBGNQ3ekXZlRhOyZL7-hnc1hi7qjSlHA%3A1571023196928&amp;ei=XOmjXaWqOKzgz7sPjpuh8Aw&amp;q=THIS+IS+A+QUERY+FOR+THE+SEARCH+SCRIPT&amp;oq=THIS+IS+A+QUERY+FOR+THE+SEARCH+SCRIPT&amp;gs_l=psy-ab.3..33i22i29i30.2534.19237..30617...7.1..2.377.10767.0j30j19j3......0....1..gws-wiz.....10..0i71j35i39j0i131i273j0j0i131j0i67j0i131i67j35i362i39j0i22i30.FHTxFzd76wY&amp;ved=0ahUKEwilyNi85ZrlAhUs8HMBHY5NCM4Q4dUDCAs&amp;uact=5</a></li>
<li>Note the protocol, the path and the script (search?), and the nightmarish query which follows.</li>
</ul>
<p>How does this translate to an IP? Well thankfully everything after the “.com”, describes a locational hierarchy which grows more specific as it goes on. These correspond to locations encoded via the IP system.</p>
<p>Thankfully there exists a third party to keep track of which URL links to which IP, specifically the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA). Whilst there exist subdivisions and subgroups, in simplified terms, IANA is an American non-profit organisation which oversees the global IP allocation and interpretation from domain names. Like the old timey phone operator connecting your call via wires in a board, the IANA can take the URL you enter into your browser and connect you to the appropriate IP.</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“<em>When </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p>Apart from the existential “whenever information is shared between two networks” or even more abstractly “whenever information is shared in a way that multiplies the resource rather than simply transferring its possession”, the internet exists at every point in time that there is either ‘traffic’ or ‘accessible destinations’.</p>
<p>Alternative answer:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>1<sup>st</sup> of January 1983</strong> = ARPANET started using TCP/IP, allowing research networks to be interconnected</li>
<li><strong>1989</strong> = Time Berners-Lee (at CERN), invented the WWW , as a more user-friendly way for scientists to share information worldwide.</li>
<li><strong>1993/1994</strong> = The first (various) web page search engines (as opposed to <em>File Transfer Protocol</em> indexes) began to spring up. These define the connectivity of the web as we know it, and were first made as an index of known useful URLs, then as searchable directories.</li>
</ul>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>Where </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p><img class="post__image--right" src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/taylor-vick-M5tzZtFCOfs-unsplash.jpg" alt="" width="3956" height="2220">In short, we might answer <em>where</em> the internet is, in terms of where the computers <em>hosting</em> IPs are. In telecommunications networks these are often referred to as ‘<em>nodes’ </em>(from the Latin for <em>knot,</em> which given the largely forgotten ‘rope net’ imagery of the internet is incredibly satisfying).</p>
<p>Whilst these can be, literally any computer with physical means of connecting to the internet (wireless or wired), it largely refers to massive warehouses of thousands of computers. </p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“<em>Whence/Whither </em>comes/goes the internet”</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/5/network.png" alt="" width="1280" height="1280">
<figcaption >Partial map of the Internet, showing IP-IP connections of 2005 by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Internet_map_1024_-_transparent,_inverted.png">The Opte Project</a>. Displaying &lt; 30% of accessible class C networks at time of investigation.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Whilst <em>Where</em> typically refers to a location (that is static and descriptive), <em>Whence</em>, a largely obsolete interrogative, means ‘from where’ (genitive/origin), while <em>Whither</em> refers to ‘to where’ (accusative/destination).</p>
<p>To access the internet, you (often unknowingly) employ your IP, as given by your ISP, to gaze upon other locations on the internet. However this IP is unique not just to your laptop/phone/PC but also to the internet connection source. By this I mean: </p>
<p><em>Is your connection a home line or via library Wi-fi, or are you using your phone’s 4G?</em></p>
<p>Each one of these will result in a different IP (be they from the same ISP company or different ISPs), as they indicate a different ‘<em>network</em> <em>location</em>’. This is because in the world of network connections, we don’t care about the physical location of a computer, but how we get information to it. </p>
<p>The physical location of a computer may affect things like <em>latency</em> (in short, time to load internet things), but if there is a working connection via the same ISP, the internet doesn’t care. For defining an IP, the journey to/from your computer to your target computer is colossally more important than their respective spatial locations.</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“<em>Why </em>is the internet?”</p>
<p>Why is there an internet? Why did we make it? Well, that’s because that’s what humans do. We share information. To do this is violently engrained in human nature. As such, when people refer to computers “<em>talking</em>” to each other, they aren’t always conscious of how excellent a metaphor this is.</p>
<p>When we lived in caves and huddled around fires to take breaks from hunting animals and carving stones, we imparted the information encoded in the neurological connections of our brains via the spoken word. This was excellent as the spoken words themselves, the sonic vibrations that wiggled through air, were shared with the listener without the speaker losing the original information. This sharing multiplied knowledge without simply transferring it.</p>
<p>We then learnt how to encode knowledge not just in our brains but visually and in written text. This text could broadcast that information from text-to-brain without destroying the text itself. Yes, one could destroy a book just as one could kill a human/brain, thus ending that node in the local shareable network of knowledge. But otherwise, that knowledge was disseminated without being destroyed.</p>
<p>Now we have a system that can share information from text-to-text. The benefit is that, as the technology we have to store texts develops, we have found types of encoding that are easier to transfer. We are not just encoding sonic text-to-person systems which can pass a few meters (kilometres if screamed). Nor are we encoding visual text-to-person which take longer to decay (as books or stone tablets are hard to break) and can be sent in the mail or carried for miles. We are now encoding data into the electromagnetic spectra which we can send zooming around the world in the blink of an eye. We send this from one non-human-person to another, who will immediately record and save the incoming data.</p>
<p>The stories we tell around a fire or the warnings of which berries not to eat, can now be brought into the future as Netflix-original online series or full botanical textbooks or university degrees by correspondence. These data are no longer sent from and received by squishy rotting organic brain-goo, and now are kept in shiny metallic rocks imbued with lighting. Not only can we impart/read information to/from these lightning rocks at our leisure, but now at our specific request, the rocks can discover knowledge on their own, that we ourselves did not have. </p>
<p>Surely to those listeners around the stone-age fire, we are inconceivable gods of knowledge. What abundance then, of data must exist in the future or to the unknowable divine, that might one day make us quake in awe, as we shake our modern animal hides and carved stones?</p>
<p>No, <em>“the internet”</em> may not be <em>real</em> in the material sense, but even if it is not <em>real</em> I think it is a thing of unquestionable beauty, if not crowning achievement of all of human evolution itself.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from stunning photograph by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Spider_web_Luc_Viatour.jpg">Luc Viatour</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Toki Pona: The lili-est Language You Haven’t Heard of Yet</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/blank-linguistics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/blank-linguistics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T17:48:55+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/4/toki-pona-banner.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p>A basic introduction to the constructed language Toki Pona and the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis. A comparison of basic Toki Pona and English sentence structure.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/4/toki-pona-banner.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>A basic introduction to the constructed language Toki Pona and the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis. A comparison of basic Toki Pona and English sentence structure.</p>

<div class="post__toc">
<h3>Table of Contents</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlfv790">What Even is Toki Pona?</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlgtgp1">How To Talk Using Only 120 Words</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlib9l2">What Even is English (Grammar)</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlkgu93">Clauses and Phrases</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlojbv4">Subjects, Predicates, and Objects</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlr26l5">Toki Time!</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlrcos6">SVO Structure</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhm0ajc7">Building Complex Concepts</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhm8e918">GEEK NOTES: Introduction to The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlfv790"><strong>What Even is Toki Pona?</strong></h2>
<p>Since my first high school Spanish lesson I realised how much I loved languages. I love learning languages. I love learning about languages. I love discovering weird quirks and paradoxes that my Anglophonic would never have considered.</p>
<p>Little did Señora Cooper know that she would nudge a small clump of ice that would snow-ball via the route of late night procrastination to a fully-fledged hobby-avalanche.</p>
<p>My newest obsession is the language Toki Pona, the world’s smallest language, a <em>ConLang</em> (constructed language).</p>
<p>Toki Pona was constructed by Sonja Elen Kisa in 2001. Since its inception it has been considered an investigation into <em>linguistic minimalism</em>, a proof of concept for the <em>Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</em>, and an application of the Taoist principle of 儉(jiǎn: frugality, simplicity, or moderation).</p>
<p>儉 (jiǎn) is one of the 三寶 (sānbǎo: three treasures/virtues), of Taoism. These 三寶 (sānbǎo) can be translated as following:</p>
<ul>
<li>慈 (cí: compassion/charity)</li>
<li>儉 (jiǎn: simplicity/frugality)</li>
<li>不敢為天下先 (bùgǎn wéi tiānxià xiān ~ “do not dare be first in the world”: humilty/modesty) </li>
</ul>
<p>(Note: these three treasures are not to be mistaken for the three treasures/jewels of Bhuddhism, Chinese medicine, of Imperial Japanese Regalia, or the Silmarils from Tolkien’s ‘The Silmarillion’)</p>
<p>Kisa’s application of 儉 (jiǎn) is what makes Toki Pona so compelling and noteworthy. Whilst many sources state that it takes around 10,000 words to attain approximate fluency of a language (a problematic simplification but nevertheless) Toki Pona only has 120 unique words. </p>
<p>That’s it. Only 120. The end*.</p>
<p>*Note that sources can cite 119-125 root words, due to obsolescence and other quirks. Nevertheless, the set I first learnt contained 120 words so this is the number I’ll refer to.</p>
<p>That’s not to say only 120 concepts can be communicated, but rather anything one wishes to say is constructed from these word roots in a structured and logical manner.</p>
<p>For example, if we were to ask how to translate the English word “coffee”, the spiritual staple on which I subsist, we would have to think for a moment. Toki Pona demands we deconstruct both WHAT and WHY we are saying what we want to say, then rebuild the concept from the 120 roots.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/4/sitelen_pona.png" alt="" width="456" height="599">
<figcaption >"sitelen pona": An alternate non-latin-alphabetical way to writing the 120 words of Toki Pona, as included by Sonja Lang in her book 'Toki Pona: The Language of Good'</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlgtgp1"><strong>How To Talk Using Only 120 Words</strong></h2>
<p>Well, if I should want to order coffee at a restaurant, and I am wanting to convey that I would like the hot dark/brown drink, I could ask for:</p>
<p class="align-center"><em>telo seli pimeja</em></p>
<p class="align-center">[water] [hot] [dark] ≈ [the hot water that is dark] ≈ “coffee”</p>
<p> Maybe I want to specify that I want the hot drink that will give me energy and keep me awake (because I forgot to study for a cardiology exam and I can’t read ECG’s for the life of me). I might then ask for:</p>
<p class="align-center"><em>telo seli wawa pi lapa ala</em></p>
<p class="align-center">[water] [hot] [power] &lt;of&gt; [sleep] [none]</p>
<p class="align-center">≈ [the hot water of power that causes no sleep]</p>
<p class="align-center">≈ “coffee”</p>
<p>Now I might go into more detail if I wanted to be certain my message wouldn’t be misunderstood and I wasn’t given a very strong tea. However, I could also go into more detail in the second description, and try to describe “coffee” somewhere along the lines of “[the hot water <u>that will give me</u> power <u>and will not allow</u> me to sleep]”, but to do so would be unnecessary and violate the spirit of Toki Pona which we might here equate to our friend儉 (jiǎn).</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlib9l2"><strong>What Even is English (Grammar)</strong></h2>
<p>Ok so now that you understand (what I at least interpret as being) the soul of this language, let’s learn a about different language entirely. <em>English</em>.</p>
<p>I remember being in high school, in Señora Cooper’s class, and having the same realisation that most people learning their first non-native language often have:</p>
<p><em>“I can speak English effortlessly and fluently, but I know NOTHING about its grammar!”</em></p>
<p>So, today let’s talk about grammar basics and how sentences <em>‘work’</em>. Once we understand this, working through Toki Pona becomes far simpler.</p>
<p> Let’s build from the ground up with our parts of a sentence:</p>
<ul>
<li>Noun = a <em>thing</em> (e.g. chair)</li>
<li>Verb = an <em>action</em> (e.g. sit)</li>
<li>Adjective = a <em>descriptor</em> (e.g. blue)</li>
</ul>
<p> Basic stuff:</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Tomatoes are red.”</p>
<p class="align-center">[Tomatoes] [are] [red]</p>
<p class="align-center">[noun] [verb] [adjective]</p>
<p>We can get more complex and throw in a pronoun (a word in place of a noun) and use a more complex verb tense structure:</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“I have been tired.”</p>
<p class="align-center">[I] [have been] [tired]</p>
<p class="align-center">[pronoun] [verb] [adjective] </p>
<p><u>Verbs and Adverbs</u></p>
<p>Now we get a bit more complex. Let’s frame our discussion in terms of <em>subjects</em> and <em>objects</em> of sentences. To do this we need to understand the two main verb types, <em>transitive</em> and <em>intransitive.</em></p>
<p>Transitive verbs affect something: <em>“I like dogs.”</em></p>
<p>Note that the verb “to like” affects or is directed at a thing (“dogs”). That is to say that this sentence has a <em>subject</em> (“I”) and an <em>object</em> (“dogs”) (In the future we will talk about <em>indirect</em> and <em>direct objects</em>.)</p>
<p>Meanwhile, intransitive verbs don’t have this kind of subject: <em>“On Sundays, David naps.” </em>Here there the juicy bit of the sentence is “<em>David naps</em>.”</p>
<p>There is a subject (“David”) but no object, meaning the verb (“naps”) is intransitive. How do we know the verb “<em>to nap</em>” is intransitive, because one can’t “<em>nap”</em> an object. You can’t “<em>nap the bed</em>”, as fun as that sounds.</p>
<p>Now you’ll note that the last sentence tells us more information about <em>when</em> “David naps.” Things that describe or give more information about a verb/action are <em>adverbs</em>. Lots of English adverbs end in “-ly” (e.g. quickly, sadly, hungrily) but others don’t (e.g. well, often, quite). However, some adverb-y bits aren’t just words, but collections of words.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhlkgu93"><u>Clauses and Phrases</u></h3>
<p>When we talk about collections of words we can refer to a:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clause = [subject] + [verb]</li>
<li>Phrase = a functional group not containing BOTH a [subject] and a [verb]. Often multiple phrases team up to make a clause.</li>
<li>Sentence = A complete concept containing at least one main clause, but often with helper (<em>subordinate</em>) clauses/phrases</li>
</ul>
<p>So when we look at:</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info"><em>“On Sundays, David naps.”</em> </p>
<p>We are looking at:</p>
<p class="align-center">[adverbial phrase], [clause]</p>
<p> One more example before we move on:</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Alex likes to eat tasty pizza, but sometimes he overindulges”</p>
<p class="align-center">[Alex likes to eat tasty pizza] [but] [sometimes he overindulges]</p>
<p class="align-center">[clause] [conjunction] [clause]</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">[Alex] {[likes][to eat]} {[tasty][pizza]} [but] [sometimes] [he] [overindulges]</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] {[verb][verb]} {object} [conjunction] [adverb] [subject] [verb]</p>
<p class="align-center">[proper noun] {transitive verb phrase} [object] [conjunction] [adverb] [pronoun] [intransitive verb]</p>
<p>What a beast of sentence analysis! But you survived. Well done.</p>
<p><strong>Fun fact: Only use a comma to break a sentence if it’s between two clauses.</strong></p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Alex likes to eat pizza, but sometimes he overindulges”</p>
<p class="align-center">“[subj][verb] but [subj][verb]”</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Alex likes to eat pizza but overindulges”</p>
<p class="align-center">note: no [subj] after the but</p>
<p>Then what’s a semicolon? It’s what you do when your clauses are independent (not linked by a conjunction) but the writer feels that the ideas are linked.</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Some days Alex orders pizza; other days David stops him.”</p>
<p> Obviously there are other uses for commas and semicolons, but those will have to wait for another day.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhlojbv4"><u>Subjects, Predicates, and Objects</u></h3>
<p>The last bit of English Grammar you need for Toki Pona is to understand what a <em>predicate</em> is.</p>
<p>It’s another way of grouping words and an alternate, more robust definition of a clause. The predicate is the action part of the sentence, but it doesn’t have to refer to a single verb. Rather, you can think of the predicate as referring to the concept of the action that the subject <em>does, </em>rather than the verb itself. How does this differ I hear you ask:</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“I like dogs.”</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [verb] [object]</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [predicate] [object] </p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info">“Tomatoes are red.”</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject][verb][adjective]</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject][predicate]</p>
<p>In the latter case, “being red” is the action [predicate] rather than “being” [verb] in a way that is red [adverb] (which I suppose one might write as “tomatoes <em>are</em> red-ly”, with red-ly being an adverb. How would one even convey that idea? <em>Tomatoes exist rubescently? Erythematously? Rufescently? Cochineally?</em>)</p>
<p>            Hmm. Back to subject-verb-object discussion.</p>
<p> English can get more complex when it feels like it, but this is our basic sentence and clause structure: {[subject] + [predicate]}. This [subject + verb +/- object] structure, SVO, for short is the basic structure of the English language; everything else gives supplementary and subordinate information.</p>
<p>In English, we call sentences with this SVO structure ‘<em>active’</em>. One example of a more complex arrangement is a <em>passive</em> structure, which in English is organized OVS</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>David opened the door</em>”</p>
<p class="align-center">[S][V][O] = Active</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>The door was opened by David</em>”</p>
<p class="align-center">[O][V][S] = Passive</p>
<p>Other languages structure differently, but thankfully for us Toki Pona only employs active SVO ordered structures.</p>
<p>That’s it. That’s your English language Primer. Now for some speedy Toki Pona.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlr26l5"><strong>Toki Time!</strong></h2>
<p class="msg msg--success"><strong><a title="http://tokipona.net/tp/janpije/dictionary.php">Here is a link to a comprehensive dictionary of toki pona's entire vocabulary, derived from Sonja Elen Kisa's book <em>'Toki Pona: The Language of Good'</em></a></strong></p>
<p>Toki Pona Ground Rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>The beginnings of sentences aren’t capitalized.</li>
<li>Verbs aren’t conjugated, meaning they don’t change for tense or person. This information is given by other parts of the sentence. (as if you were saying ‘He <u>eat</u> dinner last night’)</li>
<li>There are no articles (e.g. <em>a, an, the, some</em>)</li>
<li>Adjectives go after their nouns like in Spanish and French (<em>house red</em>, not <em>red house</em>)</li>
<li>The transition from <em>subject</em>-<em>to-predicate-to-object </em>is indicated by special grammatical units.</li>
<li>Quick’n’Dirty Pronunciation Basics: read “J” as “Y”, and stress the first syllable of each word, so “POtato" rather than the more natural “poTAto".</li>
</ul>
<p>Apart from a few purely grammatical components, most of the 120 Toki Pona root words change their job by where they are in a sentence. For example “<em>moku</em>” is the root associated with food and eating. In the place of a noun <em>moku</em> might correspond to “food”; in the place of a verb, it could mean “to eat”; as an adjective, perhaps “edible”.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhlrcos6"><u>SVO Structure</u></h3>
<p>Vocab for examples: (<em>mi</em> = I, me, my) (<em>sina</em> = You, your) (<em>moku</em> = food, eat, swallow) (<em>kili</em> = fruit/veg) (<em>toki</em> = talk, say, language) (<em>pona</em> = good, simple, well) (<em>jan</em> = person)</p>
<ul>
<li><em>li</em> = indicates moving from subject to predicate (omitted if the subject is I or You)</li>
<li><em>e</em> = indicates moving from predicate to object</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that I will use curly brackets {} to signify the omitted <em>li</em>, after I or You, to aid with sentence structure clarity.</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info"><em>jan li moku e kili</em> = people eat fruit/vegetables</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [li] [predicate] [e] [object] </p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info"><em>kili li pona</em> = Vegetables {are} good</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [li] [predicate]</p>
<p class="align-center">(note no verb, e.g. <em>‘are’/’to be’</em>, as it is implied)</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info"><em>sina {li} toki e toki pona</em> = <em>sina toki e toki pona</em> = You speak Toki Pona</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [omit: li] [predicate] [e] [object]</p>
<p class="align-center msg msg--info"><em>jan pona li toki e moku sina</em> = the good person talks to your food</p>
<p class="align-center">[subject] [li] [predicate] [e] [object]</p>
<p class="align-center">(note that <em>sina</em> is being used as an adjective, '<em>your</em>', here not a pronoun, '<em>you</em>')</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhm0ajc7"><u>Building Complex Concepts</u></h3>
<p>When the concept we want to refer to isn’t in the list of 120 words, we just construct it by joining some instead.</p>
<p>Vocab for examples (<em>ilo</em> = tool, device) (<em>musi</em> = to play, fun) (<em>lili</em> = small, young, less, short) (<em>kalama</em> = sound, noise, voice)</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Cutlery → [tool for food] → <em>ilo moku</em></p>
<p class="msg msg--info">My Friend → [a person who is good that is mine] → <em>jan pona mi</em></p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Joke → [something said that is fun] → <em>toki musi [used as a noun]</em></p>
<p class="msg msg--info">To Joke → [to say something fun] → <em>toki musi [used as a verb]</em></p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Quiet → [of a sound that is little] → <em>kalama lili</em></p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Quiet Joke / To Joke Quietly → [something said that is fun that has a sound that is small] → ???</p>
<p>Now here we might run into an issue because we want to combine</p>
<p><em>            “toki musi”</em> with<em> “kalama lili”</em> to become “<em>toki musi kalama lili”</em></p>
<p><em> </em>But depending on where we throw our brackets this could change meaning:</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">            <em>[toki musi] [kalama lili]</em> → “a joke” + “that is quiet”</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">            <em>[[toki musi] kalama] lili</em> → “a joke about sound” + “that is short”</p>
<p>Or any other potential division of these roots.</p>
<p> The natural divisions of meaning in Toki Pona word clusters involves each subsequent word being stuck onto the concept completed to the left such that:</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>A B C D E” = “[[[[A] of B] of C] of D] of E”</em> </p>
<p>So if we want to convey something else, what we do is we forcibly define where we want these brackets/groupings to be.  To do this we use <em>“[x] pi [y]”</em> which we might translate as <em>“[x] of [y]“</em> or “<em>[x] that is [y]</em> “.</p>
<p>So to say “a quiet joke” (aka “a talk-fun that-is sound-low”) we could say:</p>
<p class="msg msg--info align-center">“<em>toki musi pi kalama lili.”</em></p>
<p>Which will logically render itself as: <em>[toki musi] pi [kalama lili].</em></p>
<p>And boom. From a language which has no words for quietness or loudness or jokes or cutlery or friendship, you have created ways to say these things. This is how meaning can be encoded in Toki Pona, and therefore from those 120 roots you can encode as many concepts as you are able to construct.</p>
<p>And at the end of the day, isn’t encoding concepts the purpose of language? </p>
<p>We’ll talk about more complex Toki Pona structures in the future, but for now it’s time for geek notes.</p>
<figure class="post__image undefined" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/4/toki-pona-alt.png" width="3877" height="5107">
<figcaption >Comparison of Basic English and Toki Pona Sentence Structure</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhm8e918"><strong>GEEK NOTES: <a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/sapir-whorf-basics/">Introduction to The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</a></strong></h2>
<p>Today let’s pitch the <em>Linguistic Relativists</em> against the <em>Linguistic Universalists</em> via Toki Pona’s use of colour.</p>
<p><strong> </strong><u>The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</u></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“one's language determines one's conception of the world”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This linguistic hypothesis claims that not only do we externally vocalise our perceptions and thoughts in a manner dictated by the characteristics and breadth of our language, but that we also internally frame our thoughts in a manner dictated by our language.</p>
<p>The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis (SWH), the implications of which are often referred to as <em>Linguistic Relativity</em>, arose from the 19<sup>th</sup> and 20<sup>th</sup> century writings of Edward Sapir and Benjamin Lee Whorf (amongst others). The history of this school of thought is, as one can expect from the anthropology of the era, <em>dripping</em> in racism and notions of European political and intellectual supremacy. Nevertheless, the SWH discussed in isolation does lend itself to interesting conversations. As such I’m not going to talk much about the analysis of linguistic relativity with regards to the Inuit or Hopi peoples, because I feel that I lack the sufficient skills to extract the useful knowledge from what is otherwise a dumpster fire of flaming racist garbage.</p>
<p>So I shall return to the SWH. For this, I will choose to use the terminology I am more familiar with, that of neurology and psych:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Perception</strong> = The process of observing/being aware of an external world object stimulus and internalising it through the senses and pathways of thought to conscious and unconscious mind. “see an apple, think an apple”</li>
<li><strong>External Object</strong> = The external ‘thing’, the <em>noumenon</em>, the “apple”</li>
<li><strong>Stimulus</strong> = The external physical characteristic that can be sensed: e.g. the red light reflecting off the apple, the smell of the apple, the sound wave of a voice.</li>
<li><strong>Percept</strong> = The internal <em>phenomenon</em>, constructed in the mind. The internal image. The <em>idea</em> of that specific apple in front of you.</li>
<li><strong>Cognition</strong> = The mental process of learning and understanding, as discussed in thought, memory, perception etc.</li>
<li><strong>Thought</strong> = the flow of <em>ideas</em>, <em>associations, </em>and <em>internal objects</em> leading to a conclusion about reality.</li>
</ul>
<p>When discussing the SWH we might discuss two extents of its application, the <em>strong</em> and <em>weak</em> interpretations.</p>
<p>The strong version of the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis, deemed <em>Linguistic Determinism,</em> holds that language determines the structure and limits of thought and cognition. A rather simplified example is that our percept of an ‘apple’ is different from our percept of a ‘pear’ because we have different words for them. When see an apple or pear the higher order, more abstract, processes of perception encode the stimulus to a category which it already has available. Where there is both a word for ‘apple’ and for ‘pear’ the mind has an associated category for ‘apple’ and  for ‘pear’. As such the metaphorical admin workers can file the encoded stimulus of the red light under the ‘apple’ category. Thus the external object and it’s stimulus can be represented internally via the percept of an ‘apple’. Boom! <em>That thing is an apple!</em></p>
<p>Without this linguistic category, or even a way to subdivide larger categories (e.g. <em>sweet, red, fruit</em>), we would not have the cognitive categories to interpret these different kinds of fruit as being different. We would lose the nuance of interpretation of different fruits, and thus have a word and category that referred to all fruit. (Such as the Toki Pona <em>kili</em> = ‘fruit’, ‘vegetable’, ‘mushroom’ ≈ ‘edible plant’)</p>
<p>The weak version of the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis, deemed <em>Linguistic Influence</em>, simply holds that these linguistic categories influence but do not fully define how we think. This is admittedly easier to test experimentally in a lab with test subjects of different linguistic backgrounds. For example the standard anglophone in both reading and spatial metaphor associates the flow from left to right as analogous with past to future. When asked what word comes ‘<em>before’</em> another in a sentence, anglophones look to the left. Thus when primed with horizontal cues the anglophone will more rapidly process notions of time and order. Whereas the standard sinophone associates past with up and the future with down. For the sinophone, the associations of 上 (shàng), conceptually linked to being spatially <em>up</em> and temporally <em>previous</em> (and converse 下, xià), results in faster processing in temporal questions when primed with vertical cues.  An interesting side thought about this is, do perhaps these cognitive benefits from correct priming instead result from the associations of spatial and temporal metaphor, or because of the innate process of ingrained reading direction and the processes associated with this movement. There is consensus agreement that in the examples of English and Mandarin, the two mechanisms are not unrelated. The theory holds that the direction of writing arose from the pre-existing linguistic metaphor association, rather than the other way around.</p>
<p>A similar discussion, highlighting the division between relativist and universalist thinking, is experiments about colour perception.</p>
<p>The universalists Berlin and Kay, examined 20 languages and the way they divided colour categories. They defined a colour category as being:</p>
<ol>
<li>Monolexemic (e.g. ‘orange’ as opposed to ‘yellow-red’)</li>
<li>Monomorphemic (e.g. ‘blue’ as opposed to ‘blue-ish’</li>
<li>Not a subset of greater category (e.g. ‘green not ‘emerald’ which is a subset of green)</li>
<li>Isn’t only applicable to certain objects (e.g. ‘yellow’ as opposed to ‘blonde’)</li>
<li>Is salient for all informants (e.g. “blue” as opposed to “tiffany™-colour”)</li>
</ol>
<p>Interesting they found that for languages with fewer than 11 categories, the categories always appeared in a specific pattern as the number of total categories increased. For languages with N categories, if:</p>
<ul>
<li>N = 2, ‘black’ AND ‘white’</li>
<li>N = 3, add ‘red’</li>
<li>N = 4, add ‘green’ OR ‘yellow’ but not both</li>
<li>N = 5, add ‘green’ AND ‘ yellow’</li>
<li>N = 6, add ‘blue’</li>
<li>N = 7, add ‘brown’</li>
<li>N ≥ 8, add ‘grey’ OR ‘orange’ OR ‘pink’ OR ‘purple’</li>
</ul>
<p>Interestingly colours were found to roughly refer to the same shades across languages, as noted in the Munsell Colour System (hue, value, chroma aka colour, brightness, saturation). This seems to suggest an evolutionary agreement on which colours are important to humans, or perhaps what colour stimuli we can perceive (recalling retinal and sensory neurology).</p>
<p>We find that Toki Pona has been constructed as a N = 5, language and thus has the words: (pimeja = black) (walo = white) (loje = red) (laso = green) (jelo = yellow). As a language intentionally constructed by a linguist, it’s to be expected that this selection aligns with Berlin and Kay’s model for colour evolution.</p>
<p>But the question then arises, how do we refer to other colours in N &lt; 6 languages like Toki Pona? Two handy tricks <em>polysemy</em> and use of <em>polylexemes</em>.</p>
<p>Polysemy is the coexistence of multiple meanings (<em>sememes</em>) for a word, word-group, or word-bit (<em>morpheme</em>). This can been seen in some words in modern natural languages that have since developed N &gt; 11, but may still have polysemous words from earlier in its evolution. Some such examples are included below:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Language</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>Blue/Green Polysemy</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p>Blue Monosemy</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p>Green Monosemy</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Chinese</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E9%9D%92">青</a> (qīng) </p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E8%93%9D">蓝</a> (lán)</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E7%BB%BF">绿</a> (lǜ) </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Arabic</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p> الخضراء (al-khaḍrā')</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> أزرق (azraq)</p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p>أخضر (akhḍar)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Vietnamese</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>xanh</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Tswana</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>tala</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="112">
<p>Toki Pona</p>
</td>
<td width="163">
<p>laso</p>
</td>
<td width="144">
<p> </p>
</td>
<td width="147">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>A polylexeme is a unit made of two lexemes rammed together, as in the example “yellow-red” to mean “orange”. Vietnamese employs a similar in its Blue/Green distinctions by adding other kinds of descriptors to the root <em>xanh: </em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>xanh da trời = ‘blue’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh dương = ‘sky blue / azure’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh nước biển = ‘ocean blue’</em></li>
<li><em>xanh lá cây = ‘leaf green’</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Toki Pona can employ polylemes in these two systems of mixing and describing systems:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>loje laso</em> (blue-ish red) or <em>laso loje</em> (red-ish blue) ≈ ‘purple’</li>
<li><em>jelo loje</em> (red-ish yellow) ≈ ‘orange’</li>
</ul>
<p> OR perhaps</p>
<ul>
<li><em>loje pi telo loje </em>(red of ‘red water’) ≈ ‘blood-red’</li>
<li><em>laso kasi</em> VS <em>laso pi</em> <em>telo suli </em>(blue/green of plant/leaf VS blue/green of ‘big water’) ≈ ‘leaf-green’ VS ‘ocean-blue’</li>
</ul>
<p>So whilst the <em>linguistic relativists</em> might say that these speakers of N &lt; 6 languages view colour through the lenses and combinations of the N categories of colour and thus categories of thought, the <em>linguistic universalists</em> would instead demand every culture who can gaze upon the blue ocean will have a way to conceptualise that colour distinct from the colour of a leaf, even if they have no monolexemic monomorpheme to describe it.</p>
<p>I can’t imagine there will ever be a consensus amongst the linguists, but as a someone who sits in the sidelines watching (<em>sports metaphor—ha!)</em>, it’s fun to see what happens.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from image of <em>sitelen pona</em> from <em>Toki Pona: The Language of Good</em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Archetypes &amp; Motifs in Myth &amp; Fable </title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/archetypes-in-classics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/archetypes-in-classics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T13:29:18+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/3/archetype.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>A basic introduction to comparative mythology with discussion of motifs, themes, archetypes, the Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index, and basic Jungian psychology.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/3/archetype.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>A basic introduction to comparative mythology with discussion of motifs, themes, archetypes, the Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index, and basic Jungian psychology.</em></p>

<div class="post__toc">
<h3>Table of Contents</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlb6ll0">The Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlbjj31">The Thompson Motif Index</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhlbveh2">GEEK NOTES: Jung’s Collective Unconscious &amp; Archetypes</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlb6ll0"><strong>The Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index</strong></h2>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/3/mateus-campos-felipe-OhThddppdnY-unsplash.jpg" alt="" width="4000" height="6000">
<figcaption >
<p>"Apollo and Daphne" a marble sculpture by Gian Lorenzo Bernini, recounting a Greek myth I did NOT get to hear about in my first week of Classics.</p>
<p>This depicts the story in which Daphne would rather turn into a bay tree than hook up with a complete stranger (here being Apollo who probably wanted to rape her because basically all the male Greek gods were rapists)</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Undergrad, first week of Greek Classics.</p>
<p>Me, waiting to hear about Theseus slaying the Minotaur, or Heracles’ corpse engulfed in flames on Mount Oeta, or maybe even Zeus hoe-ing around and humping everything that moves (and maybe some things that don’t). Instead, to my outrage I am hit with a pile of readings about… Germanic fairy tales?!</p>
<p>The course was meant to be about ancient Greek Tragedies! As a frequently absent university student fond of the good nap, I had dragged by body out of bed and shown up at some heinously early (probably quite reasonable) hour, and was being presented with <em>Little Red Riding Hood</em>!</p>
<p>As my ire softened and I stopped furiously snapchatting people about my indignation, I caught wind of a discussion of the Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index (ATU Index). This is a massive catalogue of folktales, originally German but expanded beyond, which codifies and categorises folktale stories, components, and motifs.</p>
<p> The nature of stories passed via word of mouth, the oral tradition, is that the narrative is chiefly in the hands of the storyteller. Every time the tale is shared it can be twisted, certain elements forgotten, certain added or embellished, some elements just mentioned in passing. Maybe <em>Cinderella’s</em> slipper wasn’t glass but rather gold. Maybe the <em>Little Red Riding Hood</em> was too smart to be eaten by the <em>Wolf</em>, maybe she was eaten but the <em>Woodsman</em> rescued her. Maybe <em>Goldilocks’ </em>bears ate soup not porridge.</p>
<p> Do these differences matter? No. Small changes like the material of a shoe, or the culinary nature of an ursine dinner does not fundamentally change the story. So how do we categorise what is shared between different tellings of the same-ish folktale.</p>
<p> This is where the ATU Index comes in. The ATU Index, or more correctly, the ATU Index and Thompson Motif Index are a collection of tale-types, motifs, stereotyped characters and ideas in folk tales.</p>
<p> For example, categorized tales:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Little Red Riding Hood</em> (ATU 333)</li>
<li><em>Cinderella </em>(ATU 510A)
<ul>
<li>not to be mistaken for <em>Catskin</em> (ATU 510B), the similar but different narrative about a ill-treated daughter of a lord who runs away and lives as a peasant and wishes to attend a Ball against orders. She sneaks away and meets a young lord who wishes to marry her. Drama ensues.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Chinese Tale of <em>Hua Mulan</em> (ATU 514), a legendary “Shift of Sex Tale”</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlbjj31"><strong>The Thompson Motif Index</strong></h2>
<p>And for motifs we might look at Swan Lake’s use of “<em>D300-D399 Transformation: animals to person</em>”, specifically the subset “<em>D361.1 Swan maiden</em>”</p>
<p> We could apply this to a narrative arising from outside of the Germanic-Sphere. Perhaps, the tale of Aladdin with his magic Lamp (“<em>D800-D899 Ownership of magic objects</em>”) which causes “<em>D2100 Magic wealth</em>”. Or his monkey side-kick Abu in the Disney adaptation “<em>B300-B349 Helpful animals―general</em>”. We might go on to discuss his Disguise as Price Ali (“<em>K1800-K1899 Deceptions by Disguise or Illusion</em>”), and arguably if we are cynical enough “<em>K1300-K1399 Seduction or Deceptive Marriage</em>”.</p>
<p>We continue on ad nauseum, but the point is, this system allows us to see the connections between these motifs, these stories, and even these cultures in the way they handle elements of folktale.</p>
<p>How does this apply to our Ancient Greeks? Well what is the story of the titan Prometheus stealing fire from Olympus to give to humanity, and his eternal repeating punishment, if not “<em>A1100-A1699 Creation and ordering of human life</em>” and subset “<em>A1415 Theft of fire</em>” from “<em>A100-A499 Gods</em>” resulting in “<em>Q500. Tedious punishments</em>” and “<em>E670. Repeated reincarnation</em>”.</p>
<p>These motifs seem to transcend age and culture, be it the “<em>D113.1. 1 Werewolf</em>” of the historical Swiss Werewolf Trials, or the “<em>D10-D99 Transformation of man to different man</em>” of Harry Potter’s Polyjuice Potion, the “<em>C961.1 Transformation to pillar of salt for breaking taboo</em>” of the Bible’s Wife of Lot or the Greek’s Eurydice.</p>
<p>Whilst some of the vocabulary of the system is evidently grounded in Germanic folktale, the applications have extended beyond cultures. For example, concepts like <em>“G. Ogres”</em>, can be considered to include general <em>Non-Mundane Beasts</em> or perhaps <em>Demons</em>. </p>
<p>This system of analysing folktales creates a lens though which we can view all narratives. No culture’s legends are so unique that they cannot tick a couple of boxes. No ancient fable is so remote that it’s structure cannot be identified. These systems show us that humans are not so different and our stories are the same. For what is the purpose of storytelling? To explain the phenomenon of lightning to our pre-electrophysical communities? To teach our children not to walk idly in the woods on their way to Grandma? Or maybe just to keep us entertained while we huddle around the fire or drift off to sleep, dreaming of shoes made of glass and bears eating porridge. </p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhlbveh2"><strong>GEEK NOTES: <a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/jungs-archetypes/">Jung’s Collective Unconscious &amp; Archetypes</a></strong></h2>
<p>A similar concept to Aarne-Thompson-Uther indices is the Swiss Psychiatrist Carl Jung’s concept of <em>Archetypes</em>. Intellectual adversary and friend to Sigmund Freud (and potential repressed but reciprocated homo-erotic object of desire), Jung presented similar but divergent thoughts on Freud’s new field of psychoanalysis. </p>
<p>Freud’s Model of the psych consisted of three psychic apparatuses:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Id (Latin: “it”)</strong> = Disorganised instinctual component constructed of desires, impulses, and drives, present from birth. Driven by the <em>Pleasure Principle</em> to seek gratification and avoiding pain. This apparatus is completely unconscious and unknown to the conscious mind.</li>
<li><strong>The Ego (Latin: “I”)</strong> = The organised, cognitive and executive component which seeks to restrain the Id by grounding itself in the reality of the world. Driven by the <em>Reality Principle</em> to seek ways to gratify the id in a way which will maximise long term pleasure and minimise pain. This is achieved by rationalization and reason. This apparatus is largely conscious and sub/preconscious.</li>
<li><strong>The Super-Ego</strong> = The internalisation of outside world’s culture and rules. The “conscience”, the Super-Ego contradicts the Id, wanting to act with decorum and is outraged and shamed by the depravity of the Id. This apparatus spans from the conscious, via the pre-conscious, into the deep unconscious.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thus Freud could discuss mental disorders as conflicts between the <em>Ego</em> and the <em>Id </em>(<em>Transference Neuroses</em>)<em>,</em> between the <em>Ego</em> and the<em> Super-Ego</em> (<em>Narcissistic Neuroses</em>)<em>,</em> and between the <em>Ego</em> and the external world (<em>Psychoses)</em>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Jung divided the psyche into the conscious <em>Ego</em>, the <em>Personal Unconscious</em> (our recalled and repressed memories), and the <em>Collective Unconscious</em>.</p>
<p>Jung’s take, informed heavily by Eastern philosophy, was that the <em>Collective Unconscious</em> was populated by human instinct and abstractions called ‘<em>Archetypes’</em>.  Jungian psychology, now termed <em>Analytic Psychology</em>, examined how the psych strove, and more often than not failed and stagnated, to pursue its goal of self-realisation via the process of individuation, the formation of a robust and whole sense of self. The interplays between states of progress in individuation and issues encountered would be seen by analysing a patient’s dreams and thoughts. Symbolic elements of dreams for example would considered the implication of these symbolic archetypes, what they meant to the patient, and how the symbolic interplay of their narrative could be interpreted as representing psychological states.</p>
<p>These archetypes are universally relatable symbols and can be considered a simplified version of Aarne-Thompson-Uther’s motifs: A great/earth mother, a wise sage, the duality of light and dark. Some of these archetypes, being abstract symbols, can over-lap or be subsets of each other, others can be mixed flavours.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/3/Venus_de_Milo_Paris_2_September_2013_001.jpg" alt="" width="2848" height="4272">
<figcaption >
<p>The "Venus de Milo" by Alexandros of Antioche, a marble sculpture of the Greek goddess Aphrodite. When discussing the Greek gods in terms of Jungian Archetypes, Aphrodite (the embodiment of love and beauty) is a projected and symbolic incarnation of internal archetypes (here being of feminine sexuality, love, and beauty) (photo by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Venus_de_Milo,_Paris_2_September_2013_001.jpg">Tom King</a>)</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>These internal archetypes are projected onto the external world as simplified way of viewing complex ideas. June Singer discussed some more well-studied archetypes in terms of opposites, one set pertaining to the <em>Ego</em> the other to the abstract notion of the <em>Shadow</em>. Light (ego) is opposed by Darkness (shadow), the Old Wise Man (ego) is opposed by the Trickster (shadow), the Great Mother (ego) is opposed by the Tyrannical Father (shadow), et cetera. The implication of the Chinese philosophy of Yin and Yang, is unmistakable.</p>
<p>Jung however would argue that the metaphysics and cosmologies of eastern philosophy, of astrology, of alchemy, of mythology, all of which he was well versed in, were simply the human psyche projecting these archetypical symbols onto external phenomena. The process of Alchemy, it’s various procedures, were imbued with the symbols of the internal psych, with the progress towards <em>The Great Work</em> of Alchemy (e.g. formation of the <em>Philosopher’s Stone) </em>marked by a progress of archetypical symbols towards <em>The Great Work</em> of personal psychology: Self-Realisation.</p>
<p>So what are these archetypes? Well given the ethereal and blended nature, delineating individual and unique archetypes is difficult, and at times down-right futile. Nevertheless a number of Jungian psychologists, mystics, artists, and anthropologists have tried.</p>
<p>In his posthumously compiled works <em>Archetypes of the Collective Unconscious</em>, Jung explicitly refers to 12 main archetypes, whilst acknowledging the existence of many others:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Self</li>
<li>The Anima</li>
<li>The Animus</li>
<li>The Shadow</li>
<li>The Persona</li>
<li>The Father</li>
<li>The Mother</li>
<li>The Child</li>
<li>The Wise Old (Sage)</li>
<li>The Hero</li>
<li>The Trickster</li>
<li>The Maiden</li>
</ul>
<p>In Margaret Mark and Carol Pearson’s book <em>The Hero and the Outlaw</em> a guide to distinct branding directed by principles of myth and pop-psychology define a different 12 archetypes:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Innocent</li>
<li>The Orphan</li>
<li>The Hero</li>
<li>The Caregiver</li>
<li>The Explorer</li>
<li>The Rebel</li>
<li>The Lover</li>
<li>The Creator</li>
<li>The Jester</li>
<li>The Sage</li>
<li>The Magician</li>
<li>The Ruler </li>
</ul>
<p>This has been used also as a system of personality typing and alignment. Largely popular personality typing systems can be considered to employ ideas of archetypes such as: personality enneagrams, various zodiacs, Myer’s Briggs personality types etc.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from an <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Greek_Eros_vase.png">attic red vase</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Propagating Pothos &amp; Why We Prune</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/pothos-basics/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/pothos-basics/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T17:48:09+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/2/pothos.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>How to care for and propagate "Golden Pothos" (Epipremnum aureum), the world's best houseplant. How to prune pothos and the science of why it can be beneficial.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/2/pothos.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>How to care for and propagate "Golden Pothos" (Epipremnum aureum), the world's best houseplant. How to prune pothos and the science of why it can be beneficial.</em></p>

<div class="post__toc">
<p>Table of Contents</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkj6es0">My Pothos Baby</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkjdsu1">Basic Pothos Care</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhl4fjob">How to Grow Pothos</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkk23j3">So What of Pruning? </a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkklfa4">Propagating Pothos</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkl3vr5">Water vs Soil Rooting</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkm2406">Water-to-Soil</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkmhlv7">Soil-to-Water</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhkmqrg8">GEEK NOTES: Introduction to Phytohormones</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhkj6es0"><strong>My Pothos Baby</strong></h2>
<p>I have always been a fan of buying myself a houseplant to mark the news: new school, new apartment, new degree, new city. There was something about the idea of another living thing sharing the new period of growth and change with me that felt reassuring. Naturally, the downside to this was when poorly cared for plants died and I assumed portended a terrible omen for that period. Perhaps it wasn’t a wise emotional investment considering how little I knew about plant-care.</p>
<p>In the time before I fell in love with botany, I did still love house plants, I just never had any idea how to properly cultivate or propagate them. As such I managed to kill most of little crazy-student-omen-bringers. That is of course, except for one I purchased upon moving to Melbourne for med school. My pride and joy…</p>
<p><em>Epipremnum aureum</em>, aka ‘Golden Pothos’ (or more commonly ‘Devil’s Ivy’ in Australia).</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhkjdsu1"><strong>Basic Pothos Care</strong></h2>
<br><img class="post__image--right" src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/2/patrick-perkins-ab_Ds2rBqNU-unsplash.jpg" width="385" height="312">It’s hard have access to Google and an interest in houseplants without being inundated on articles about <em>Epipremnum aureum</em>. Why? Because they are, in my humble opinion, the perfect house plant: they look gorgeous, are easy to grow, hard to kill, they clean the air (pulling various toxic hydrocarbons from the air), and they’re bonkers-easy to propagate. So in the noble tradition of online plant-folk here are some thoughts on cultivating <em>Epipremnum aureum<strong>.</strong></em>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhl4fjob"><u>How to Grow Pothos</u></h3>
<p><img class="post__image--right" src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/2/kevin-lessy-aKqw_M1CmfI-unsplash.jpg" width="348" height="464">It is worth noting that the care of many vining species of certain genera is often grouped together, frequently: <em>Epipremnum</em>, <em>Scindapsus,</em> and to a lesser extend the vining <em>Philodendron </em>and<em> Peperomia species.</em> This is because they like similar conditions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Partial to medium shade</li>
<li>Dry-out periods between thorough watering</li>
<li>Frequent pruning to promote leaf density</li>
<li>Seasonal fertilising (if you are so inclined, but they can happily survive for quite some time without fertilising)</li>
</ul>
<p>What does this mean for the amateur botanist or forgetful student? As long as it’s not baking in the sun, you can water it, forget about it, have it dry out a fair amount, remember your pot plant, freak out, give it a good dousing, and return to forgetting about it.</p>
<p>Like I said, the perfect house plant.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhkk23j3"><u>So What of Pruning? </u></h3>
<p>Growing upwards-creeping vines, is Pothos’ preferred state, though obviously not necessary, if it’s not how you want to cultivate yours. Whilst I’m not recommending you attempt to recreate and entire Polynesian forest, Pothos does tend to do well growing attached to stakes, poles, walls, or other plants. As it does this, your plant can’t help but harken back to its days on the island of Mo’orea, setting out tendrils as it reaches to the sun. In this quest it can focus less on developing additional leaves and spend more of its energy stretching ever forward along its course and making existing leaves larger.As a vine native to the temperate forests of French Polynesia, Pothos developed to like warm areas, whilst still growing happily in the shade as it wound it’s ways up the pacific flora via its climbing aerial roots.</p>
<p>What this means for you, is that longer vines become what plant-folk call “leggy”. That is, longer expanses between nodes (from which sprout leaves and aerial roots). Whilst this is desirable for some looks, others may want fuller more dense foliage. To achieve this we prune.</p>
<p>When discussing vines I prefer using terminology from human anatomy, here “proximal” and “distal”, rather than trying to work out what is “above” or “below” when talking about cuttings. Here “proximal” refers to being closer to the base of the plant and its water/soil roots, and “distal” refers to being closer to the end/tip of a vine. Simple.</p>
<p>To prune your Pothos, simply cut just distal (I prefer around 1 inch distal) to a node (the area where leaves and/or aerial roots sprout, often visually similar to the edge of band on a bamboo plant). Ideally you’d be cutting on a 45* angle with sterilised pruning shears, but in my experience clean scissors and a sloppily angled cut is typically fine. </p>
<p>Don’t worry about hurting your Pothos, as they don’t just tolerate being pruned, but thrive in response to it, focusing on consolidating closer to their base.</p>
<p>But now what to do with your cuttings? Well, yet another reason we all love <em>Epipremnum aureum</em>, is that it’s cuttings desperately want to form roots, all thanks to those handy aerial roots.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhkklfa4"><strong>Propagating Pothos</strong></h2>
<p>If you’re wanting to root a Pothos cutting, which I absolutely recommend you do, you need to pay attention to where incision(/s) are taking place relative to nodes and aerials. </p>
<ol>
<li>Cut 1 inch proximal to a node. To propagate a single leaf, cut 1 inch distal to that same node. Feel free to cut back the parent vine, ½ an inch distal of the last node if you don’t like the naked internode segment end.</li>
</ol>
<p>Given that the aerials are the parts of the vine best suited to becoming water-roots these are our focus. Depending on how you’d like to propagate you can take a cutting of a single leaf by cutting about one inch proximal and distal to its node, or of a larger vine segment. If you opt for the latter I recommend stripping one or two leaves off the vine from the distal end of the cutting leaving one/two nodes to become roots to support the vine.</p>
<p>In my experience both single leaf and vine propagation are fine, one produces more plants, the other produces a more developed plant and looks far more elegant if water-rooting. Which brings me to…</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhkl3vr5"><u>Water vs Soil Rooting</u></h3>
<p>Pothos doesn’t require any additional hormones to take root, just a medium to grow in. There are two main approaches that exist, water and soil rooting. Both work. Both have their benefits. Both have their downfalls.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Decide to water or soil propagate</li>
</ol>
<p> As a rule of thumb a plant propagated in water will want to remain in water, and one growing in soil will want to remain in soil. Thus the transforming water-to-soil roots or soil-to-water roots requires a degree care as not shock the plant so much it wilts and dies.</p>
<p>To water propagate simply plop your cutting plain room temperature tap water, leaves above water, at least one root below. And wait.</p>
<p>To soil propagate plant your cutting such that the vine and root are below soil, and keep the soil moist. Not ‘wet’ such that a paper towel touching the surface will suck up a massive spot of water, but such that the aerial root has enough moisture to understand it is now dark and damp and it’s been assigned a new job. For me in a Melbourne summer this would involve watering a small pot maybe every 3 days.</p>
<p>In both cases we want our plants warm but not burning in direct sunlight, having their developing roots never fully dry, and NOT fertilised at all costs. Whilst some plant fertilisers <em>may</em> be fine, they are a) not necessary, and b) may cause more harm than good, with some fertilisers being damaging to newly transformed ex-aerial roots. </p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Weekly maintenance</li>
</ol>
<p>Water propagated plants will need their water changed regularly (ideally weekly, though I have been known to ‘set and forget’ for months on end). This reduces the chances of accidentally culturing some weird fungal moment, and increases the amount of oxygen available to the growing roots dissolved in the water. Stagnation is the enemy here. </p>
<p>With soil propagation it is expected that for the first week or so the cutting may start to look a little wilt-y and a spot glum, not on the brink of death but not as perky as it had been. This makes sense, it has been previous receiving a stream of water from its vine, and now may be a little thirsty as its newly developing roots try to provide enough water the cutting. In my experience after this week, assuming the medium hasn’t dried out, the cuttings will either perk back up (a sign that we’re in business and the aerials are beginning to transform) or will wilt further (a sign that this cutting will likely not make it). Yellowing of the leaf (or all the leaves if a longer cutting) on the other hand means that this cutting has fully given up and its best to start again. That’s ok. This happens.</p>
<p>If you’re having luck you can pull back the watering a bit. Not to the extent of the parent plant. For me this would mean my 3 day watering would pull back to weekly (as opposed to 1-2 weekly for the parent). Keep in mind this depends on the temperature, the soil, and the size of the pot (bigger pot, more soil, longer to dry out).</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>End point</li>
</ol>
<p>For water propagation this is when you see your roots being established. I like my single leaves to have an 1-2 inches of roots, and longer vines to have maybe 2-4 inches depending on the size of the cutting. However a point to keep in mind is that the longer the root, the harder the plant has to work to transform itself to a soil environment.</p>
<p>For soil propagation I wait for new growth. Any baby leaves, any nubs, nodes, bobbles, or bits. If they’re green and the plant is laying down new tissue we’ve got a winner. The  cutting can now be kept in the pot or moved to a new pot. Over the next month or so I’d pull back to water cycles comparable to the parent plant (judging of course by the soil moisture and/or leaf signs not the number of days between watering) </p>
<ol start="5">
<li>(Optional) Root Transformation</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhkm2406"><u>Water-to-Soil</u></h3>
<p>I prefer water propagation because not only does the process look cooler, allow visual monitoringing of root progress, but in my experience has had a higher yield of cuttings successfully rooting.</p>
<p>Whilst you can leave your new vine in water indefinitely, it will grow much happier in soil with all it’s beautiful nutrients. However the path from water to soil root can be perilous. </p>
<p>There are many techniques for this transformation but given the strong hardy nature of  <em>Epipremnum aureum</em> I typically bypass the more delicate and finicky approaches. Instead I care only about two things: Root Integrity, and Water Control. </p>
<p>When moving to soil, you need to remember that the water roots are soft, squishy, unprotected, and prone to damage. To avoid this I pay the recipient pot with soil leaving a space for the plant, hold the plant by the vine above this space such that the delicate roots can fall into it, and gently spoon soil into the opening, never directly applying pressure to the roots. </p>
<p>I then take a ramped-up approach to watering as with soil-to-soil propagation. Start very wet, keeping in mind these roots are used to full water submersion. I aim for damp water, not quite having a visible water level, knowing that you would pull out a wet finger if you shoved it in. </p>
<p>Over the course of a month I transition from wet to damp to moist. If at any time after the first week you see new growth forming you can speed up this process. After about a month I’m confident that my new plants have either made the transition or begun to wilt, and I can pull back to regular Pothos watering.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhkmhlv7"><u>Soil-to-Water</u></h3>
<p>I am yet to find a highly successful method of transition. Thankfully I am also yet to find a compelling reason to make such a transition. I have only ever made such a transition out of curiosity and can see no other reason why one would ever uproot a healthy soil-rooted plant into water.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, this involves remove the plant and root ball form the pot, transferring it to a bucket of room temperature water. Via slight jiggling and root separation, let the soil fall away from the roots. Once the roots are sufficiently clean for your taste, transfer to its new watery-home</p>
<p>In my (minimal) experience, smaller plants tolerate this change better, which I attributed to the larger (now unmet) nutrient requirements of larger soil-rooted plants.</p>
<figure class="post__image undefined" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/2/Pothos1.png" width="2759" height="3676">
<figcaption >Summary of Water Propagation of Pothos</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhkmqrg8"><strong>GEEK NOTES: <a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/phytohormones-basics/">Introduction to Phytohormones</a></strong></h2>
<p>But why prune in the first place? As mentioned above, it helps promote more proximal growth and development of the plant, but how? The easy answer that “the plant can spend more energy on growing wide as opposed to tall”, whilst charmingly personifying doesn’t actually help to explain the increased rate of lateral growth. Furthermore it doesn’t really provide any mechanistic justification for not just simply letting your plant grow un-pruned until it has achieved the desired lateral development.</p>
<p> And yet we see pruning the most distal parts seems to promote lateral growth. Why is that? To answer this, let’s have a quick refresher on plant endocrinology.</p>
<p><u>Plant Hormone Basics</u></p>
<p>There are five major groups of <em>phytohormones </em>(plant hormones) discussed in modern botany:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Abscisic Acid </em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Auxins</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Cytokinins</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Ethylene</em></strong></li>
<li><strong><em>Gibberellins</em></strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Below is a (very basic) description of what they do.</p>
<p><strong><em>Abscisic Acid</em> (ABA)</strong> is the chief water stress signal. When roots detect that water is at a critical level they release ABA into the plant vasculature. Similar to a human <em>neurotransmitters</em> and neural <em>action potential</em> functioning, ABA triggers an influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and <em>membrane depolarisation</em> of stomatal <em>guard cells</em> (the cells which open/close <em>stomata</em>, the microscopic windows in a leaf which allow water and air to be breathed in and out of the plant). This results in efflux of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, and associated anions. The loss of these ions, draws water out of the guard cells, mediating stomatal closure, reducing potential water losses by <em>transpiration</em>.</p>
<p> At this point it is worth mentioning the topic of <em>Meristems</em>, locations of embryonic plant tissue capable of dividing and growing branches/roots. <em>Meristematic</em> <em>tissue</em> can be located apically (end of stems/vines/roots) or lateral (branch points).</p>
<p><strong><em>Auxins</em></strong> care about length over width. This is to say they promote <em>apical dominance</em>, longer stems and roots with less lateral/axillary budding. Produced chiefly in the apical meristems, Auxins signal for lateral buds (dormant embryonic <em>meristems</em>) to remain dormant, causing growth to be predominantly apical rather than lateral. Thus in the case of <em>Epipremnum aureum </em>pruning, we are removing apical meristems, promoting development of lateral buds, and overall fullness of the plant, rather than length.</p>
<p> In a related manner, <em>Auxin</em> is the chief of <em>phototropism</em>, the curving growth of plants towards a light source. Produced in the stem tip, Auxin localises to the darker side of the plant. Thus, when the auxin promotes more pronounced growth on this side, the overall effect is to arch the stem towards the light. The same processes facilitates <em>gravitropism </em>(aka <em>geotropism</em>), the growth of root in the direction of gravity by gravitationally-dictated auxin distribution in the roots. This is the process which is being exploited by exogenous <em>Auxin</em> when industrial ‘Rooting Hormone’ is added to plants or cuttings.</p>
<p><strong><em>Cytokinins</em></strong> (not to be mistaken for human kinins of the <em>Kinin-Kallikrein system</em>) promote cell division and inhibit aging of greenery. Their function is far too complex to attempt even a basic discussion here, but in short, Cytokinins work in a system of balances and ratios with Auxin to drive embryonic patterning and differentiation, <em>callus</em> formation.</p>
<p><strong><em>Ethylene </em></strong>(aka Ethene in organic chemistry, H<sub>2</sub>C=CH<sub>2</sub>)  is the cause of the proverbial ‘rotten apple’ spoiling the bunch, and ripe bananas ‘infecting’ green bananas with their ripe-ness. The only known gaseous plant hormone, <em>Ethylene</em> signals for the opening of flowers, the ripening of fruit, the shedding (<em>abscission</em>) of leaves, and ultimately rotting of proverbial apples. The culmination of a series of biosynthetic operations and the <em>Methionine/Yang cycle</em> (which gives me <em>Citric Acid/Krebb’s</em> undergrad war flashbacks), <em>Ethylene</em> is formed by the oxidation of ACC. Thus the agricultural world has found that keep produce in high-CO<sub>2</sub>, low-O<sub>2</sub> environments reduces ripening and rotting.</p>
<p><strong><em>Gibberellins </em></strong>(GAs) main concern is <em>internode</em> elongation, with lesser roles in germination, differentiation, and embryonic patterning, and synthesised in areas of active plant growth. Plants with low/defective/inhibited <em>GAs</em> present with <em>brachytic</em> <em>dwarfism</em> (internodal shortening). This causes short stems and close clustering of nodes (and thus leaves/branches/flowers etc). Conversely <em>GA</em> excess results in long stems, sparse branching, and elongated plants. The understanding of this hormone plays an important role in forming high-yielding varieties of agricultural goods (dwarf cereals, elongated sugarcane).</p>
<p>So<em>, </em>whenever we hear someone discussing plant-pruning in the name of lateral growth, we can thank our little friends<em> Auxins</em> and<em> Gibberellins</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from photo by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Money_plant_(Epipremnum_aureum)_1.jpg">Mokkie</a> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kidney Stones 101: Struvites &amp; Staghorns</title>
        <author>
            <name>Alexander Nathan</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/kidney-stones-101/"/>
        <id>https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/kidney-stones-101/</id>

        <updated>2019-10-21T13:30:22+11:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/kidney-stones.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p><em>Written for non-medical folk: Basic kidney function and disease process causing kidney stones. Discussion of role of dehydration, salts, and the urinary tract.</em></p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/kidney-stones.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><em>Written for non-medical folk: Basic kidney function and disease process causing kidney stones. Discussion of role of dehydration, salts, and the urinary tract.</em></p>

<div class="post__toc">
<p>Table of Contents</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk5b8fa">What Even Are Kidney Stones?</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk5fi5b">What Should The Kidneys Do?</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk5sndc">What Shouldn’t They Do?</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk66h4d">A Stone!! Now What?</a></li>
<li><a href="#mcetoc_1dnhk6jlhe">GEEK NOTES (Med Student Study Notes): Nephrolithiasis Basics</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhk5b8fa"><strong>What Even Are Kidney Stones?</strong></h2>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhk5fi5b"><strong>What Should The Kidneys Do?</strong></h3>
<p>The human body is, in a manner of speaking, a walking sack of blood. When we talk about how much blood we usually cite the number 5L. Not perfect, but near enough for us. Every day the heart pumps this around your body at an amazing rate: 7200L pumping through your heart daily. </p>
<p>Of that 7200L, 75% is sent by the heart to the tissues of the body. This blood brings the brain, muscles, and organs their supply of oxygen, sugar, and all the chemicals they needs. Meanwhile the blood carries away all of the garbage from the cells that they don’t want, chiefly: carbon dioxide, urea, creatinine, various salts, and all the excess water and other chemicals they've absorbed or created. Now before we go any further, know that when I say “<em>salts</em>” I’m not necessarily talking about the those white crystals you might add to your dinner, rather the category of chemical compounds of which <em>table salt (iodinised NaCl)</em> is a member.</p>
<p>The remaining 25% (1800L/day) goes to the kidneys. Their job is to let all the fluid bits of the blood into their tubules and keep all the big bulky cells and proteins in the blood. From these tubules, the important stuff that your body wants to hold onto is reabsorbed back into the blood. The remaining fluid, the unwanted salts, chemicals, and toxins are passed to the bladder and eventually urinated out.</p>
<p>However, the handy thing is that the kidneys can absorb things differently depending on what the body needs. If you’re dehydrated, they will reabsorb more water, making more concentrated urine. Thus, the bladder fills with a more concentrated, darker urine, that’s packed with more of those salts, toxins/waste chemicals, and lose less of that precious water.</p>
<p>To be honest, I think that’s pretty cool.</p>
<div class="gallery"   >
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1127.png" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1127-thumbnail.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1127" width="417" height="700"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Renal Coronal Section: An old-timey cross-section image of a kidney, because Gray's Anatomy (20e) is public domain, so why not?</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1120.png" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1120-thumbnail.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1120" width="683" height="900"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Abdominal view showing the kidneys in place (much of the internal viscera in front of the kidneys has not been displayed)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1121.png" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1121-thumbnail.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1121" width="538" height="600"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Abdominal &amp; Pelvic view showing both kidneys, their attached ureters, and the top of the bladder peaking out the bottom.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1130.png" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/gallery/Gray1130-thumbnail.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1130" width="188" height="250"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Glomerulus: This displays one of the kidney's many glomeruli (bottom), a twisty knot of capillaries from which fluid can flow into the renal tubule (top) and through the kidneys long tubulue system.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dnhk5sndc"><strong>What Shouldn’t They Do?</strong></h3>
<p>However to keep doctors in business, sometimes things in the body have to go wrong. Thankfully for the doctors, the human body is magnificent... but beautifully imperfect.</p>
<p>When the kidneys are reabsorbing the water they want (from inside the kidney’s tubules back into the blood), they concentrate all those unwanted chemicals. Sometimes the highly concentrated toxins/salts can play havoc on the kidneys. Such chemicals can include some toxins, some medications, and some salts absorbed from food: </p>
<ul>
<li>Calcium oxalate, the most common cause of kidney stones, formed from the breakdown of a chemical in some foods.</li>
<li>Struvite, commonly forming stones in women with frequent UTIs (the most common cause of large multi-branched stones called <strong><em>STAGHORN</em></strong> calculi (calculi being Latin for stones).</li>
<li>Uric acid, the chemical that causes the crystals in gout.</li>
<li>Cysteine, typically in people with the genetic disorder cystinuria.</li>
</ul>
<p>When one of these dissolved salts is highly concentrated it can crystallise INSIDE the tubules of the kidney. What this means, is that like a shiny urinary snowball, a small number of these salt molecules clump together to form a solid stone. This stone gets bigger and bigger as more salt molecules join the party. Next thing you know, there’s a massive stone sitting in your kidney.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhk66h4d"><strong>A Stone!! Now What?</strong></h2>
<p>In short. It’s not great. Pain. And often infections.</p>
<p>Just like normal urine the body tries to pass the stones from the kidneys, down connecting pipes called the <em>ureters,</em> into the bladder. From the bladder, when it’s time to urinate, the body aims to pass the urine (and any stones) through the <em>urethra</em> to the outside world (and hopefully flushed down the plumbing). However typically, somewhere in this process the stone can get stuck. This hurts. A lot, many women comparing it (and describing it as worse that) childbirth.</p>
<p>Whilst smaller stones can often pass on their own (with a weirdly strong degree of evidence suggesting this are aided greatly by a patient going on a roller coaster), larger stones may need medical, interventional, or even surgical help.</p>
<p>As always, if you think you might have a kidney stone, are in any pain, or are concerned about your health in the short or long term, go see a doctor. If you're in crippling agony, skip down to your local <em>Emergency Department </em>post haste. If you're not currently in extreme pain but have some concerns, go see your <em>GP</em>.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight align-left">If you don't have a regulary GP, which I absolutely recommend you do if you can, I suggest you find an affordable/bulk-billing clinic to regularly attend just so you are on their local files. This <em>IMMENSELY</em> helps the doctors do their jobs better.</p>
<p><em>[Summary Infographic on it's way]</em></p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1dnhk6jlhe">GEEK NOTES (Med Student Study Notes):  <a href="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/nephrolithiasis/">Nephrolithiasis Basics</a></h2>
<p><u>Stone Types and Urinary Chemical Causes</u></p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/Gray1122.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1122" width="515" height="400">
<figcaption >Spatial relationship between kidneys and their neighbouring viscera</figcaption>
</figure>
<ul>
<li><strong>Calcium Oxalate (75%)</strong> ↑ Calcium ↑ Oxalate ↑ Urate ↑ Citrate
<ul>
<li>Oxalate: meat, dietary sodium, nuts, beans, cruciferous vegetables, fatty acid malabs (Crohn’s), high vit C, low B6</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Uric Acid (10%)</strong> ↑ Urate
<ul>
<li>Aciduria</li>
<li>Uric Acid: Alcohol, seafood, fatty and organ meats</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Struvite (5%)</strong> ↑ Urease Positive UTIs
<ul>
<li>Proteus mirabilis, Klebsiella, Pseudomonas UTIs</li>
<li>Form largest stones, including STAGHORN calculi (which fill the renal pelvis and calyces)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Calcium Phosphate</strong> ↑ Calcium ↑ Phosphate</li>
<li><strong>Cystine</strong> ↑ Cysteine (familial cysteinuria)</li>
</ul>
<p> <u>Epidemiology</u></p>
<p>General Risk Factors</p>
<ul>
<li>♂ &gt; ♀</li>
<li>30-60 years old</li>
<li>Dehydration</li>
<li>+ve FHx or PHx</li>
</ul>
<p>Stone-Specific Risk Factors </p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p class="align-center"><strong> </strong></p>
</td>
<td class="align-center" width="94">
<p><strong>Risk Factors</strong></p>
</td>
<td colspan="4" width="377">
<p class="align-center"><strong>Prevention</strong></p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Calcium Oxalate</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↑ Calcium</p>
<p>↑ Oxalate</p>
<p>↑ Citrate</p>
<p>↓ Urine pH</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Sufficient Dietary Calcium*</p>
<p>↓ Oxalate Rich Food</p>
</td>
<td rowspan="2" width="94">
<p>↓ Dietary salt ↓ Animal proteins    Thiazide diuretics (for isolated  cases of ↑ urinary calcium</p>
</td>
<td rowspan="5" width="94">
<p>↑ Water</p>
<p>&gt; 2½ L/d</p>
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Calcium Phosphate</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↑ PTH</p>
<p>Type 1 RTA</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary acidisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Uric Acid</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>↓ Urine pH</p>
<p>↑ Urate</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Allopurinol</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p> </p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Struvite</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urease + UTI</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary acidisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>UTI prevention and treatment</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="94">
<p><strong>Cystine</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Cystinuria</p>
</td>
<td width="94">
<p>Urinary alkalinisation</p>
</td>
<td width="94"> </td>
<td width="94"> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>* low calcium intake increases oxalate reabsorption </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right" ><img src="https://djeasey.github.io/staghorn-blog/media/posts/1/Gray1128.png" alt="Gray's Anatomy (20e) Plate 1128" width="602" height="600">
<figcaption >A nephron schematic, because who doesn't love a good nephron schematic?</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Note that the three locations that stones are most likely to get ‘stuck’ are:</p>
<ul>
<li>the pelvi-ureteric junction (PUJ)</li>
<li>the ureter enters the pelvis (crossesing the common iliac artery bifurcation)</li>
<li>the vesicoureteric junction (VUJ)</li>
</ul>
<p><u>Clinical Presentation and Diagnosis</u></p>
<ul>
<li>Symptoms
<ul>
<li>Paroxysmal progressive unilateral flank colic</li>
<li>Radiation: to lower abdomen, groin, labia, testicles, perineum</li>
<li>Haematuria</li>
<li>Nausea/Vomiting</li>
<li>Dysuria, Frequency, Urgency</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Signs
<ul>
<li>Observed haematuria</li>
<li>Reduced bowel sounds</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Investigations
<ul>
<li>WBC (?UTI)</li>
<li>BUN, Creatinine (?AKI)</li>
<li>Dipstick (?UTI, pH &gt;7 ?Urease +)</li>
<li>Urine Microscopy + Straining (?Crystals)
<ul>
<li>Dumbbell/Octahedron (?Oxalate)</li>
<li>Rhomboid/Needles (?Urate)</li>
<li>Coffin-Prism (?Struvite)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Urine Culture (?UTI)</li>
<li>Bloods (UEC, PTH, Urate, HCO3, ALP)</li>
<li>Nonenhanced CT Abdo-Pelvis (Gold-Standard)
<ul>
<li>Calculus size, site, densite, obstruction, hydronephrosis)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ultrasound (pregnant, children, gynae/abdo DDx)</li>
<li>KUB X-Ray
<ul>
<li>Radiopaque = Calcium-containing</li>
<li>Weakly + = Struvite or Cysteine</li>
<li>Radiolucent = Urate</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Intravenous pyelogram</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Differentials
<ul>
<li>Testicular torsion</li>
<li>Acute abdomen</li>
<li>Hydronephrosis</li>
<li>UTI</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><u>Management</u></p>
<ul>
<li>?Complicated Urolithiasis
<ul>
<li>High-grade hydronephrosis</li>
<li>Pyelonephritis</li>
<li>Urosepsis</li>
<li>AKI</li>
<li>Vomiting or Intractable Pain</li>
<li>&lt; 4w of Stone Hx</li>
<li>Failed medical therapy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Stable Pt, Uncomplicated Stone, &lt;10mm
<ul>
<li>Support and Surveil</li>
<li>Hydrate</li>
<li>NSAIDs, IV Morph</li>
<li>Tamsulosin (a-blocker) or Nifedipine (CCB)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Uterorenoscopy + Extracorporal Shockwave Lithotripsy  for &lt; 20mm</li>
<li>Percutaneous Nephrolithotomy for &gt;20mm</li>
<li>Complicated Cases
<ul>
<li>Ureteral stenting or percutaneous nephrostomy (pyelo/hydro-decompression)</li>
<li>Shock Wave Lithotripsy</li>
<li>Last resort = laproscopic or open surgical removal (e.g. staghorn stones)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p id="mcetoc_1dnhk890bf">If known stone cause = Urine pH Modification</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><u>Prognosis and Complications</u></p>
<ul>
<li>&lt;5mm often to pass spontaneously,</li>
<li>&gt;10mm typically won’t, especially if ureteric sphincter or proximal.</li>
<li>50% 10 year relapse rate</li>
<li>Complications
<ul>
<li>Recurrent UTI → pyelonephritis, urosepsis, and perinephric abscess</li>
<li>Obstruction → hydronephrosis → glomerular damage</li>
<li>Acute kidney injury</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Banner image edited from glomerulus micrograph by <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Renal_corpuscle.jpg">Ed Uthman</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
